<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
    xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
    xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">

    <channel>
        <title>NASA</title>
        <atom:link href="https://www.nasa.gov/news-release/feed/" rel="self"
            type="application/rss+xml" />
        <link>https://www.nasa.gov</link>
        <description>Official National Aeronautics and Space Administration Website</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 15:22:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <language>en-US</language>
        <sy:updatePeriod>
            hourly </sy:updatePeriod>
        <sy:updateFrequency>
            1 </sy:updateFrequency>
        <generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
        <item>
            <title>Chandra Catches Spider Pulsars Destroying Nearby Stars</title>
            <link>
                https://www.nasa.gov/image-article/chandra-catches-spider-pulsars-destroying-nearby-stars/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Lee Mohon]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 15:14:43 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Chandra X-Ray Observatory]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Hubble Space Telescope]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Marshall Space Flight Center]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Neutron Stars]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Pulsars]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Spitzer Space Telescope]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[The Universe]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nasa.gov/?post_type=image-article&#038;p=572899</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[A group of dead&#160;stars&#160;known as “spider pulsars” are obliterating companion stars within their reach. Data from&#160;NASA’s Chandra X-ray Observatory&#160;of the&#160;globular cluster&#160;Omega Centauri is helping astronomers understand how these spider pulsars prey on their stellar companions. A&#160;pulsar&#160;is the spinning dense core that remains after a massive star collapses into itself to form a&#160;neutron star. Rapidly rotating [&#8230;]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="padding-top-5 padding-bottom-3 width-full maxw-full hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-article-intro"><div class="width-full maxw-full article-header"><div class="margin-bottom-2 width-full maxw-full"><p class="label carbon-60 margin-0 margin-bottom-3 padding-0">4 min read</p><h1 class="display-48 margin-bottom-2">Preparations for Next Moonwalk Simulations Underway (and Underwater)</h1></div></div></div>

<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img fetchpriority="high" width="2048" height="2048" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="A cluster brimming with millions of stars glistens like an iridescent opal in this image from NASA&#039;s Spitzer Space Telescope. Called Omega Centauri, the sparkling orb of stars is like a miniature galaxy. It is the biggest and brightest of the 150 or so similar objects, called globular clusters, that orbit around the outside of our Milky Way galaxy. Stargazers at southern latitudes can spot the stellar gem with the naked eye in the constellation Centaurus. Globular clusters are some of the oldest objects in our universe. Their stars are over 12 billion years old, and, in most cases, formed all at once when the universe was just a toddler. Omega Centauri is unusual in that its stars are of different ages and possess varying levels of metals, or elements heavier than boron. Astronomers say this points to a different origin for Omega Centauri than other globular clusters: they think it might be the core of a dwarf galaxy that was ripped apart and absorbed by our Milky Way long ago. In this new view of Omega Centauri, Spitzer&#039;s infrared observations have been combined with visible-light data from the National Science Foundation&#039;s Blanco 4-meter telescope at Cerro Tololo Inter-American Observatory in Chile. Visible-light data with a wavelength of .55 microns is colored blue, 3.6-micron infrared light captured by Spitzer&#039;s infrared array camera is colored green and 24-micron infrared light taken by Spitzer&#039;s multiband imaging photometer is colored red. Where green and red overlap, the color yellow appears. Thus, the yellow and red dots are stars revealed by Spitzer. These stars, called red giants, are more evolved, larger and dustier. The stars that appear blue were spotted in both visible and 3.6-micron-, or near-, infrared light. They are less evolved, like our own sun. Some of the red spots in the picture are distant galaxies beyond our own." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=150,150 150w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=300,300 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=768,768 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=1024,1024 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=1536,1536 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=2048,2048 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=50,50 50w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=100,100 100w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=200,200 200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=400,400 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=600,600 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=900,900 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=1200,1200 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders.jpg?resize=2000,2000 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" loading="eager" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-credits">X-ray: NASA/CXC/SAO; Optical: NASA/ESA/STScI/AURA; IR:NASA/JPL/Caltech; Image Processing: NASA/CXC/SAO/N. Wolk</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>A group of dead&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/xray_sources/stars.html" rel="noopener">stars</a>&nbsp;known as “spider pulsars” are obliterating companion stars within their reach. Data from&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/about/" rel="noopener">NASA’s Chandra X-ray Observatory</a>&nbsp;of the&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/resources/glossaryG.html" rel="noopener">globular cluster</a>&nbsp;Omega Centauri is helping astronomers understand how these spider pulsars prey on their stellar companions.</p>



<p>A&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/xray_sources/neutron_stars.html" rel="noopener">pulsar</a>&nbsp;is the spinning dense core that remains after a massive star collapses into itself to form a&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/xray_sources/neutron_stars.html" rel="noopener">neutron star</a>. Rapidly rotating neutron stars can produce beams of&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/resources/glossaryR.html" rel="noopener">radiation</a>. Like a rotating lighthouse beam, the radiation can be observed as a powerful, pulsing source of radiation, or pulsar. Some pulsars spin around dozens to hundreds of times per second, and these are known as millisecond pulsars.</p>



<p>Spider pulsars are a special class of millisecond pulsars, and get their name for the damage they inflict on small companion stars in orbit around them. Through winds of energetic particles streaming out from the spider pulsars, the outer layers of the pulsar’s companion stars are methodically stripped away.</p>



<p>Astronomers recently discovered 18 millisecond pulsars in Omega Centauri — located about 17,700 light-years from Earth — using the Parkes and MeerKAT radio telescopes. A pair of astronomers from the University of Alberta in Canada then looked at Chandra data of Omega Centauri to see if any of the millisecond pulsars give off&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/xray_astro/xrays.html" rel="noopener">X-rays</a>.</p>



<p>They found 11 millisecond pulsars emitting X-rays, and five of those were spider pulsars concentrated near the center of Omega Centauri. The researchers next combined the data of Omega Centauri with Chandra observations of 26 spider pulsars in 12 other globular clusters.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img width="2048" height="1488" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="A close-up image of Omega Centauri, in X-ray &amp; optical light, shows the locations of some of the spider pulsars. Spider pulsars are a special class of millisecond pulsars, and get their name for the damage they inflict on small companion stars in orbit around them." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=300,218 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=768,558 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=1024,744 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=1536,1116 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=2048,1488 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=400,291 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=600,436 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=900,654 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=1200,872 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/spiders-inset-labeled.jpg?resize=2000,1453 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">A close-up image of Omega Centauri, in X-ray &amp; optical light, shows the locations of some of the spider pulsars. Spider pulsars are a special class of millisecond pulsars, and get their name for the damage they inflict on small companion stars in orbit around them.</div><div class="hds-credits">X-ray: NASA/CXC/SAO; Optical: NASA/ESA/STScI/AURA; Image Processing: NASA/CXC/SAO/N. Wolk</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>There are two varieties of spider pulsars based on the size of the star being destroyed. “Redback” spider pulsars are damaging companion stars weighing between a tenth and a half the mass of the Sun. Meanwhile, the “black widow” spider pulsars are damaging companion stars with less than 5 percent of the Sun’s mass.</p>



<p>The team found a clear difference between the two classes of spider pulsars, with the redbacks being brighter in X-rays than the black widows, confirming previous work. The team is the first to show a general correlation between X-ray brightness and companion mass for spider pulsars, with pulsars that produce more X-rays being paired with more massive companions. This gives clear evidence that the mass of the companion to spider pulsars influences the X-ray dose the star receives.</p>



<p>The X-rays detected by Chandra are mainly thought to be generated when the winds of particles flowing away from the pulsars collide with winds of matter blowing away from the companion stars and produce&nbsp;<a href="https://chandra.si.edu/resources/glossaryS.html" rel="noopener">shock waves</a>, similar to those produced by supersonic aircraft.</p>



<p>Spider pulsars are typically separated from their companions by only about one to 14 times the distance between the Earth and Moon. This close proximity — cosmically speaking — causes the energetic particles from the pulsars to be particularly damaging to their companion stars.</p>



<p>This finding agrees with theoretical models that scientists have developed. Because more massive stars produce a denser wind of particles, there is a stronger shock — producing brighter X-rays — when their wind collides with the particles from the pulsar. The proximity of the companion stars to their pulsars means the X-rays can cause significant damage to the stars, along with the pulsar’s wind.</p>



<p>Chandra&#8217;s sharp X-ray vision is crucial for studying millisecond pulsars in globular clusters because they often contain large numbers of X-ray sources in a small part of the sky, making it difficult to distinguish sources from each other. Several of the millisecond pulsars in Omega Centauri have other, unrelated X-ray sources only a few arc seconds away. (One arc second is the apparent size of a penny seen at a distance of 2.5 miles.)</p>



<p>The paper describing these results will be published in the December issue of the Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, and a preprint of the accepted paper is&nbsp;<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13189" rel="noopener">available online</a>. The authors of the paper are Jiaqi (Jake) Zhao and Craig Heinke, both from the University of Alberta in Canada.</p>



<p>NASA&#8217;s Marshall Space Flight Center manages the Chandra program. The Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory&#8217;s Chandra X-ray Center controls science operations from Cambridge, Massachusetts, and flight operations from Burlington, Massachusetts.</p>



<p><a href="https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2023/spiders/" rel="noopener">Read more from NASA’s Chandra X-ray Observatory.</a></p>



<p>For more Chandra images, multimedia and related materials, visit:</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission/chandra-x-ray-observatory/">https://www.nasa.gov/mission/chandra-x-ray-observatory/</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">News Media Contact</h2>



<p><a href="mailto:mwatzke@cfe.harvard.edu">Megan Watzke</a><br>Chandra X-ray Center<br>Cambridge, Mass.<br>617-496-7998</p>



<p><a href="mailto:jonathan.e.deal@nasa.gov">Jonathan Deal</a><br>Marshall Space Flight Center<br>Huntsville, Ala.<br>256-544-0034</p>
]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Webb Study Reveals Rocky Planets Can Form in Extreme Environments</title>
            <link>
                https://www.nasa.gov/missions/webb/webb-study-reveals-rocky-planets-can-form-in-extreme-environments/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[steve sabia]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 15:01:06 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Exoplanets]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Goddard Space Flight Center]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Nebulae]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Planetary Nebulae]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Stars]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Terrestrial Exoplanets]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[The Universe]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nasa.gov/?p=573312</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[An international team of astronomers has used NASA’s James Webb Space Telescope to provide the first observation of water and other molecules in the highly irradiated inner, rocky-planet-forming regions of a disk in one of the most extreme environments in our galaxy. These results suggest that the conditions for terrestrial planet formation can occur in [&#8230;]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="hds-article-hero-header nasa-gb-align-full bg-carbon-90 width-full maxw-full color-mode-dark hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-article-hero-header">		<div class="hds-cover-wrapper width-full maxw-full minh-tablet grid-container minh-tablet flex-column padding-0">
			<div class="hds-foreground-wrapper display-flex flex-direction-column">
				<div class="grid-container grid-container-block margin-top-auto width-full maxw-desktop-lg padding-y-9 padding-x-3 desktop:padding-x-0 z-400">
					<div class="z-400 grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-7 z-400">
						<div class="margin-0">
							<div class="label color-spacesuit-white margin-bottom-2">5 Min Read</div>
							<h1 class="heading-41 line-height-md color-spacesuit-white-important">
								Webb Study Reveals Rocky Planets Can Form in Extreme Environments							</h1>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div class="grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5"></div>
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-left mobile-skrim-top z-200"></div>
					<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?w=1280" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536" alt="The image is dominated by a dusty disk extending from upper left to lower right and tilted toward the viewer. It resembles patchy clouds with small rocky bits scattered throughout. At 4 o’clock and 11 o’clock are two small, embedded planets. The outer edges of the disk are reddish, the middle orange, and the inner region yellow-white. At the center is a gap within which is a bright white star." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.4); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg 1280w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=400,225 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=600,338 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></figure>				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="padding-y-3 padding-x-3">
			<div class="grid-container grid-container-block padding-x-0">
							</div>
		</div>
	</div>


<p>An international team of astronomers has used NASA’s James Webb Space Telescope to provide the first observation of water and other molecules in the highly irradiated inner, rocky-planet-forming regions of a disk in one of the most extreme environments in our galaxy. These results suggest that the conditions for terrestrial planet formation can occur in a possible broader range of environments than previously thought. </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Image: Protoplanetary Disk (Artist Concept)</h2>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?w=1280" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="The image is dominated by a dusty disk extending from upper left to lower right and tilted toward the viewer. It resembles patchy clouds with small rocky bits scattered throughout. At 4 o’clock and 11 o’clock are two small, embedded planets. The outer edges of the disk are reddish, the middle orange, and the inner region yellow-white. At the center is a gap within which is a bright white star." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg 1280w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=400,225 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=600,338 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfq5yxz04pf608hqb0krtf3s.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">This is an artist’s impression of a young star surrounded by a protoplanetary disk in which planets are forming. </div><div class="hds-credits">ESO/L. Calçada</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>These are the first results from the eXtreme Ultraviolet Environments (XUE) James Webb Space Telescope program, which focuses on the characterization of planet-forming disks (vast, spinning clouds of gas, dust, and chunks of rock where planets form and evolve) in massive star-forming regions. These regions are likely representative of the environment in which most planetary systems formed. Understanding the impact of environment on planet formation is important for scientists to gain insights into the diversity of the different types of exoplanets.</p>



<p>The XUE program targets a total of 15 disks in three areas of the Lobster Nebula (also known as NGC 6357), a large emission nebula roughly 5,500 light-years away from Earth in the constellation Scorpius. The Lobster Nebula is one of the youngest and closest massive star-formation complexes, and is host to some of the most massive stars in our galaxy. Massive stars are hotter, and therefore emit more ultraviolet (UV) radiation. This can disperse the gas, making the expected disk lifetime as short as a million years. Thanks to Webb, astronomers can now study the effect of UV radiation on the inner rocky-planet forming regions of protoplanetary disks around stars like our Sun.</p>



<p>“Webb is the only telescope with the spatial resolution and sensitivity to study planet-forming disks in massive star-forming regions,” said team lead María Claudia Ramírez-Tannus of the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy in Germany.</p>



<p>Astronomers aim to characterize the physical properties and chemical composition of the rocky-planet-forming regions of disks in the Lobster Nebula using the Medium Resolution Spectrometer on Webb’s Mid-Infrared Instrument (<a href="https://esawebb.org/about/instruments/miri/" rel="noopener">MIRI</a>). This first result focuses on the protoplanetary disk termed XUE 1, which is located in the star cluster Pismis 24.</p>



<p>“Only the MIRI wavelength range and spectral resolution allow us to probe the molecular inventory and physical conditions of the warm gas and dust where rocky planets form,” added team member Arjan Bik of Stockholm University in Sweden.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Image: XUE 1 spectrum detects water</h2>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?w=1280" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Graphic titled “XUE 1 Irradiated Protoplanetary Disk, MIRI Medium -Resolution Spectroscopy” shows a graph of brightness versus wavelength from 13.3 to 15.5 microns, with acetylene, hydrogen cyanide, water, and carbon dioxide peaks highlighted." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg 1280w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?resize=400,225 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?resize=600,338 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfpt6zchm0y1jphbk8d4hs62.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">This spectrum shows data from the protoplanetary disk termed XUE 1, which is located in the star cluster Pismis 24. The inner disk around XUE 1 revealed signatures of water (highlighted here in blue), as well as acetylene (C2H2, green), hydrogen cyanide (HCN, brown), and carbon dioxide (CO2, red). As indicated, some of the emission detected was weaker than some of the predicted models, which might imply a small outer disk radius.</div><div class="hds-credits">NASA, ESA, CSA, M. Ramírez-Tannus (Max Planck Institute for Astronomy), J. Olmsted (STScI)</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>Due to its location near several massive stars in NGC 6357, scientists expect XUE 1 to have been constantly exposed to high amounts of ultraviolet radiation throughout its life. However, in this extreme environment the team still detected a range of molecules that are the building blocks for rocky planets.</p>



<p>“We find that the inner disk around XUE 1 is remarkably similar to those in nearby star-forming regions,” said team member Rens Waters of Radboud University in the Netherlands. “We’ve detected water and other molecules like carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide, hydrogen cyanide, and acetylene. However, the emission found was weaker than some models predicted. This might imply a small outer disk radius.”</p>



<p>“We were surprised and excited because this is the first time that these molecules have been detected under these extreme conditions,” added Lars Cuijpers of Radboud University. The team also found small, partially crystalline silicate dust at the disk’s surface. This is considered to be the building blocks of rocky planets.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These results are good news for rocky planet formation, as the science team finds that the conditions in the inner disk resemble those found in the well-studied disks located in nearby star-forming regions, where only low-mass stars form. This suggests that rocky planets can form in a much broader range of environments than previously believed.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Image: XUE 1 Spectrum detects CO</h2>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?w=1280" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Graphic titled “XUE 1 Irradiated Protoplanetary Disk, MIRI Medium -Resolution Spectroscopy” shows a graph of brightness versus wavelength from 4.95 to 5.15 microns, with carbon monoxide peaks highlighted." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg 1280w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?resize=400,225 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?resize=600,338 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/stsci-01hfptk93qpatd1q966xda0xcs.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">This spectrum shows data from the protoplanetary disk termed XUE 1, which is located in the star cluster Pismis 24. It features the observed signatures of carbon monoxide spanning 4.95 to 5.15 microns. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA, ESA, CSA, M. Ramírez-Tannus (Max Planck Institute for Astronomy), J. Olmsted (STScI)</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p><br>The team notes that the remaining observations from the XUE program are crucial to establish the commonality of these conditions.</p>



<p>“XUE 1 shows us that the conditions to form rocky planets are there, so the next step is to check how common that is,” said Ramírez-Tannus. “We will observe other disks in the same region to determine the frequency with which these conditions can be observed.”</p>



<p><a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ad03f8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">These results have been published </a>in <em>The Astrophysical Journal</em>.</p>



<p><em>The James Webb Space Telescope is the world&#8217;s premier space science observatory. Webb is solving mysteries in our solar system, looking beyond to distant worlds around other stars, and probing the mysterious structures and origins of our universe and our place in it. Webb is an international program led by NASA with its partners, ESA (European Space Agency) and the Canadian Space Agency.</em></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Media Contacts</h2>



<p><strong>Laura&nbsp;Betz</strong> &#8211; <a href="mailto:laura.e.betz@nasa.gov">laura.e.betz@nasa.gov</a>, <strong>Rob Gutro</strong>&#8211; <a href="mailto:rob.gutro@nasa.gov">rob.gutro@nasa.gov</a><br>NASA’s <em>&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nasa.gov/goddard" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Goddard Space Flight Center</em></a>,&nbsp;</em>, Greenbelt, Md.</p>



<p><strong>Bethany Downer  &#8211; &nbsp;</strong><a href="mailto:Bethany.Downer@esawebb.org">Bethany.Downer@esawebb.org</a><strong><br></strong>ESA/Webb Chief Science Communications Officer</p>



<p><strong>Christine Pulliam</strong> <a href="mailto:cpulliam@stsci.edu">cpulliam@stsci.edu</a><br>Space Telescope Science Institute, Baltimore, Md.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Downloads</h2>



<p><strong><a href="https://webbtelescope.org/contents/news-releases/2023/news-2023-152#section-id-2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Download full resolution images for this article</a></strong>  from the Space Telescope Science Institute.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ad03f8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Research results published</a> </strong>in <em>The Astrophysical Journal</em>.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Related Information</h2>



<p><strong><a href="https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/what-is-an-exoplanet/planet-types/terrestrial/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Terrestrial Exoplanets</a></strong></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/what-is-an-exoplanet/overview/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Exoplanets 101</a></strong></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/life-and-death/intro/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LIfe and Death of a Planetary System</a></strong></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/" rel="noopener">Webb Mission</a></strong> &#8211;  https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/latestnews/" rel="noopener">Webb News</a></strong> &#8211; https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/latestnews/</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/multimedia/images/" rel="noopener">Webb Images</a></strong> &#8211;  https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/multimedia/images/</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Related For Kids</h2>



<p><strong><a href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/planet-what-is/en/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">What is a Planet?</a></strong></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/all-about-exoplanets/en/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">What is an Exoplanet?</a></strong></p>



<p><strong><a href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/other-solar-systems/en/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">How Many Solar Systems are in our Galaxy?</a></strong></p>



<p><a href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/galaxy/en/" rel="noopener"><strong>What Is a Galaxy?</strong></a></p>



<p><a href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/james-webb-space-telescope/en/" rel="noopener"><strong>What is the Webb Telescope?</strong></a></p>



<p><a href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/" rel="noopener"><strong>SpacePlace for Kids</strong></a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">En Español</h2>



<p><a href="https://ciencia.nasa.gov/" rel="noopener"><strong>Ciencia de la NASA</strong></a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/es/"><strong>NASA en español&nbsp;</strong></a></p>



<p><a href="https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/sp/" rel="noopener"><strong>Space Place&nbsp;para niños</strong></a></p>


<div id="" class="hds-topic-cards nasa-gb-align-full maxw-full width-full padding-y-6 padding-x-3 color-mode-dark hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-topic-cards">		<div class="grid-container grid-container-block-lg padding-x-0">
			<div class="grid-row flex-align-center margin-bottom-3">
				<div class="desktop:grid-col-8 margin-bottom-2 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
					<div class="label color-carbon-60 margin-bottom-2">Keep Exploring</div>
					<h2 class="heading-36 line-height-sm">Related Topics</h2>
				</div>
			</div>
				<div class="grid-row grid-gap-2 hds-topic-cards-wrapper">
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/james-webb-space-telescope/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<h3 class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>James Webb Space Telescope</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</h3>
							<p class="margin-bottom-0 margin-top-2 color-carbon-20-important">Webb is the premier observatory of the next decade, serving thousands of astronomers worldwide. It studies every phase in the&hellip;</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp" ></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/exoplanets/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<h3 class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Exoplanets</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</h3>
							<p class="margin-bottom-0 margin-top-2 color-carbon-20-important">Overview Most of the exoplanets discovered so far are in a relatively small region of our galaxy, the Milky Way.&hellip;</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/lp79118d-beautyshot-jpg.webp" ></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/universe/stars/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<h3 class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Stars</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</h3>
							<p class="margin-bottom-0 margin-top-2 color-carbon-20-important">Overview Stars are giant balls of hot gas – mostly hydrogen, with some helium and small amounts of other elements.&hellip;</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/may102022-x1pt5flare-171-131-304-jpg.webp" ></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/astrophysics/focus-areas/what-are-galaxies/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<h3 class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Galaxies</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</h3>
							<p class="margin-bottom-0 margin-top-2 color-carbon-20-important">Our galaxy, the Milky Way, is typical: it has hundreds of billions of stars, enough gas and dust to make&hellip;</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/deep_field-1.jpg" ></figure>									</div>
			</a>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>

<div id="" class="nasa-gb-align-full width-full maxw-full padding-x-3 padding-y-0 hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-credits-and-details">
<section class="padding-x-0 padding-top-5 padding-bottom-2 desktop:padding-top-7 desktop:padding-bottom-9">
	<div class="grid-row grid-container maxw-widescreen padding-0">
		<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-2 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
			<div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black">
				<div class="margin-bottom-2">
					<h2 class="heading-14">Share</h2>
				</div>
				<div class="padding-bottom-2">
					<ul class="social-icons social-icons-round">
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-x">
							<a href="https://x.com/intent/tweet?via=NASA&#038;text=Webb%20Study%20Reveals%20Rocky%20Planets%20Can%20Form%20in%20Extreme%20Environments&#038;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nasa.gov%2Fmissions%2Fwebb%2Fwebb-study-reveals-rocky-planets-can-form-in-extreme-environments%2F" aria-label="Share on X.">
								<svg width="1200" height="1227" viewBox="0 0 1200 1227" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M714.163 519.284L1160.89 0H1055.03L667.137 450.887L357.328 0H0L468.492 681.821L0 1226.37H105.866L515.491 750.218L842.672 1226.37H1200L714.137 519.284H714.163ZM569.165 687.828L521.697 619.934L144.011 79.6944H306.615L611.412 515.685L658.88 583.579L1055.08 1150.3H892.476L569.165 687.854V687.828Z" fill="white"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-facebook">
							<a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nasa.gov%2Fmissions%2Fwebb%2Fwebb-study-reveals-rocky-planets-can-form-in-extreme-environments%2F" aria-label="Share on Facebook.">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M9 8h-3v4h3v12h5v-12h3.642l.358-4h-4v-1.667c0-.955.192-1.333 1.115-1.333h2.885v-5h-3.808c-3.596 0-5.192 1.583-5.192 4.615v3.385z"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-linkedin">
							<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/shareArticle?mini=true&#038;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nasa.gov%2Fmissions%2Fwebb%2Fwebb-study-reveals-rocky-planets-can-form-in-extreme-environments%2F" aria-label="Share on LinkedIn.">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M4.98 3.5c0 1.381-1.11 2.5-2.48 2.5s-2.48-1.119-2.48-2.5c0-1.38 1.11-2.5 2.48-2.5s2.48 1.12 2.48 2.5zm.02 4.5h-5v16h5v-16zm7.982 0h-4.968v16h4.969v-8.399c0-4.67 6.029-5.052 6.029 0v8.399h4.988v-10.131c0-7.88-8.922-7.593-11.018-3.714v-2.155z"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-rss">
							<a href="/feed/" aria-label="Subscribe to RSS feed.">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 800 800" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M493 652H392c0-134-111-244-244-244V307c189 0 345 156 345 345zm71 0c0-228-188-416-416-416V132c285 0 520 235 520 520z"/><circle cx="219" cy="581" r="71"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
					</ul>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
			<div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black">
				<div class="margin-bottom-2">
					<h2 class="heading-14">Details</h2>
				</div>
				<div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3">
					<div class="grid-col-4">
						<div class="subheading">Last Updated</div>
					</div>
					<div class="grid-col-8">Nov 30, 2023</div>
				</div>
			<div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3"><div class="grid-col-4"><div class="subheading">Editor</div></div><div class="grid-col-8">steve sabia</div></div><div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3"><div class="grid-col-4"><div class="subheading">Contact</div></div><div class="grid-col-8"><div class="margin-bottom-3"><div>Laura Betz</div><div></div></div></div></div>			</div>
		</div>
	<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0"><div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black "><div class="margin-bottom-2"><h2 class="heading-14">Related Terms</h2></div><ul class="article-tags"><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb" rel="noopener">James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/exoplanets/" rel="noopener">Exoplanets</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/goddard/">Goddard Space Flight Center</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/nasa-missions/">Missions</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/universe/nebulae/">Nebulae</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/universe/nebulae/planetary-nebulae/">Planetary Nebulae</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/universe/stars/" rel="noopener">Stars</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/universe/exoplanets/terrestrial/">Terrestrial Exoplanets</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/universe/" rel="noopener">The Universe</a></li></ul></div></div>
	</div>
</section>
	</div>]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Deputy for Electrified Aircraft Propulsion Integration Joe Connolly</title>
            <link>
                https://www.nasa.gov/image-article/deputy-for-electrified-aircraft-propulsion-integration-joe-connolly/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Thalia K. Patrinos]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 14:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nasa.gov/?post_type=image-article&#038;p=572481</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[“The goal is to get as many of the wrong ideas out of the way as early as possible.&#160; &#8220;So we&#8217;ll come up with some idea, especially on the research side, and sometimes it will seem really brilliant on the napkin or in a conversation with one other person.&#160; &#8220;[When I started working on electric [&#8230;]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1365" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg 3000w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/grc-2023-c-10506-1.jpg?resize=2000,1333 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure></div></div></div>


<p>“The goal is to get as many of the wrong ideas out of the way as early as possible.&nbsp;<br><br>&#8220;So we&#8217;ll come up with some idea, especially on the research side, and sometimes it will seem really brilliant on the napkin or in a conversation with one other person.&nbsp;<br><br>&#8220;[When I started working on electric aircraft propulsion,] I was not familiar with all of the electrical&nbsp;ins&nbsp;and outs. I thought power would just be available, and I could use it when I wanted it.&nbsp;[Our concepts had]&nbsp;all these little hiccups — how they get integrated in the real system, how the battery systems are going to interplay, and all the extra safety things that we need to consider—they&nbsp;allowed us to figure out things a little bit earlier and [give us] a broader perspective.<br><br>&#8220;The key thing is that when you&#8217;re working on something that&#8217;s really hard, I think the whole expectation is that you&#8217;re going to fail. So we try to fail as many times as we can early on. So when we&#8217;re getting closer to an actual demonstration, we&#8217;re pretty confident that at that point, we&#8217;ve talked to the right people, everyone&#8217;s on board, and we&#8217;re going to have a safe, larger test campaign.<br><br>&#8220;It&#8217;s always better to fail earlier on and learn as much as you can.”<br><br>— Joe Connolly, Deputy for&nbsp;Electrified Aircraft Propulsion Integration, Glenn Research Center</p>



<p></p>



<p><em>Image Credit: NASA / Jef Janis<br>Interviewer: NASA / Thalia Patrinos</em></p>



<p><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/gallery/faces-of-nasa/">Check out some of our other Faces of NASA.</a></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Discovery Alert: Watch the Synchronized Dance of a 6-Planet System</title>
            <link>
                https://science.nasa.gov/missions/tess/discovery-alert-watch-the-synchronized-dance-of-a-6-planet-system/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 02:44:14 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Exoplanets]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[TESS (Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite)]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[The Universe]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">
                https://science.nasa.gov/missions/tess/discovery-alert-watch-the-synchronized-dance-of-a-6-planet-system/</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[Six “sub-Neptune” exoplanets orbit their star in a kind of rhythmic dance – one easily set to music.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 class="wp-block-heading">Discovery Alert: Watch the Synchronized Dance of a 6-Planet System</h1>
<p><strong>The discovery:</strong> Six planets orbit their central star in a rhythmic beat, a rare case of an “in sync” gravitational lockstep that could offer deep insight into planet formation and evolution.</p>
<p><strong>Key facts:</strong> A star smaller and cooler than our Sun hosts a truly strange family of planets: six “sub-Neptunes” – possibly smaller versions of our own Neptune – moving in a cyclic rhythm. This orbital waltz repeats itself so precisely it can be readily set to music.</p>
<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image">
<div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline">
<div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto">
<figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><video class="hds-video-background" alt="" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 92% 0%; object-position: 92% 0%; object-fit: cover;" autoplay="true" loop="true" muted="true"><source src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hd110067-discovery-animation-compressed-simpler.mp4" type="video/mp4" /></video></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2">
<div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">This animation shows six “sub-Neptune” exoplanets in rhythmic orbits around their star – with a musical tone as each planet passes a line drawn through the system. The line is where the planets cross in front of (transit) their star from Earth’s perspective. In these rhythms, known as “resonance,” the innermost planet makes three orbits for every two of the next planet out. Among the outermost planets, a pattern of four orbits for every three of the next planet out is repeated twice. </div>
<div class="hds-credits">Animation credit: Dr. Hugh Osborn, University of Bern</div>
</figcaption></div>
</div>
</div>
<p><strong>Details:</strong> While multi-planet systems are common in our galaxy, those in a tight gravitational formation known as “resonance” are observed by astronomers far less often. In this case, the planet closest to the star makes three orbits for every two of the next planet out – called a 3/2 resonance  –  a pattern that is repeated among the four closest planets.</p>
<p>Among the outermost planets, a pattern of four orbits for every three of the next planet out (a 4/3 resonance) is repeated twice. And these resonant orbits are rock-solid: The planets likely have been performing this same rhythmic dance since the system formed billions of years ago. Such reliable stability means this system has not suffered the shocks and shakeups scientists might typically expect in the early days of planet formation – smash-ups and collisions, mergers and breakups as planets jockey for position. And that, in turn, could say something important about how this system formed. Its rigid stability was locked in early; the planets’ 3/2 and 4/3 resonances are almost exactly as they were at the time of formation. More precise measurements of these planets’ masses and orbits will be needed to further sharpen the picture of how the system formed.</p>
<p><strong>Fun facts:</strong> The discovery of this system is something of a detective story. The first hints of it came from NASA’s TESS (the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite), which tracks the tiny eclipses – the “transits” – that planets make as they cross the faces of their stars. Combining the TESS measurements, made in separate observations two years apart, revealed an assortment of transits for the host star, called HD 110067. But it was difficult to distinguish how many planets they represented, or to pin down their orbits.</p>
<p>Eventually, astronomers singled out the two innermost planets, with orbital periods – “years” – of 9 days for the closest planet, 14 days for the next one out. A third planet, with a year about 20 days long, was identified with the help of data from CHEOPS, The European Space Agency’s CHaracterising ExOPlanets Satellite.</p>
<p>Then the scientists noticed something extraordinary. The three planets’ orbits matched what would be expected if they were locked in a 3/2 resonance. The next steps were all about math and gravity. The science team, led by Rafael Luque of the University of Chicago, worked through a well-known list of resonances that potentially could be found in such systems, trying to match them to the remaining transits that had been picked up by TESS. The only resonance chain that matched up suggested a fourth planet in the system, with an orbit about 31 days long. Two more transits had been seen, but their orbits remained unaccounted for because they were only single observations (more than one transit observation is needed to pin down a planet’s orbit). The scientists again ran through the list of possible orbits if there were two additional, outer planets that fit the expected chain of resonances across the whole system. The best fit they found: a fifth planet with a 41-day orbit, and a sixth just shy of 55.</p>
<p>At this point the science team almost hit a dead end. The slice of the TESS observations that had any chance of confirming the predicted orbits of the two outer planets had been set aside during processing. Excessive light scattered through the observation field by Earth and the Moon seemed to make them unusable. But not so fast. Scientist Joseph Twicken, of the SETI Institute and of the NASA Ames Research Center, took notice of the scattered light problem. He knew that scientist David Rapetti, also of Ames and of the Universities Space Research Association, happened to be working on a new computer code to recover transit data thought to be lost because of scattered light. At Twicken’s suggestion, Rapetti applied his new code to the TESS data. He found two transits for the outer planets – exactly where the science team led by Luque had predicted.</p>
<p><strong>The discoverers: </strong>An international team of researchers led by Rafael Luque, of the University of Chicago, published a paper online on the discovery, “A resonant sextuplet of sub-Neptunes transiting the bright star HD 110067,” in the journal Nature on Nov. 29.</p>
<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image">
<div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline">
<div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto">
<figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-none "><img fetchpriority="high" width="2048" height="1365" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048 not-transparent" alt="An illustration shows a planetary orrery of six colorful exoplanets around their star. There is also a key showing planetary pairs and how their orbits are time in a resonance. The planets' s paths are shown in colorful lines of synchronization." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;--dominant-color: #1c1511;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg 2048w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hdresonance.jpg?resize=2000,1333 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" loading="eager" data-has-transparency="false" data-dominant-color="1c1511" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2">
<div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Tracing a link between two neighbour planet at regular time interval along their orbits, creates a pattern unique to each couple. The six planets of the HD110067 system create together a mesmerising geometric pattern due to their resonance-chain.</div>
<div class="hds-credits">Credit: Thibaut Roger/NCCR PlanetS, CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div>
</figcaption></div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>The Marshall Star for November 29, 2023</title>
            <link>
                https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/marshall/the-marshall-star-for-november-29-2023/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Lee Mohon]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 23:40:46 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Marshall Space Flight Center]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nasa.gov/?p=573039</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[Artemis II Crew Enjoys Visit with Marshall Team Members By Wayne Smith From talking about continuing the legacy of NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center in space exploration to describing their roles in an upcoming historic mission, Artemis II astronauts enjoyed visiting with center team members Nov. 27. The crew will be the first to ride [&#8230;]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="hds-article-hero-header nasa-gb-align-full bg-carbon-90 width-full maxw-full color-mode-dark hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-article-hero-header">		<div class="hds-cover-wrapper width-full maxw-full minh-tablet grid-container minh-tablet flex-column padding-0">
			<div class="hds-foreground-wrapper display-flex flex-direction-column">
				<div class="grid-container grid-container-block margin-top-auto width-full maxw-desktop-lg padding-y-9 padding-x-3 desktop:padding-x-0 z-400">
					<div class="z-400 grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-7 z-400">
						<div class="margin-0">
							<div class="label color-spacesuit-white margin-bottom-2">15 Min Read</div>
							<h1 class="heading-41 line-height-md color-spacesuit-white-important">
								The Marshall Star for November 29, 2023							</h1>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div class="grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5"></div>
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-left mobile-skrim-top z-200"></div>
					<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1536" height="1053" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?w=1536" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536" alt="From left, Artemis II astronauts Jeremy Hansen, Christina Koch, and Victor Glover listen as Commander Reid Wiseman talks during an employee event at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center on Nov. 27." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 52% 51%; object-position: 52% 51%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg 3513w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=300,206 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=768,526 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=1024,702 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=1536,1053 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=2048,1404 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=400,274 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=600,411 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=900,617 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=1200,823 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=2000,1371 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1536px) 100vw, 1536px" /></figure>				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="padding-y-3 padding-x-3">
			<div class="grid-container grid-container-block padding-x-0">
							</div>
		</div>
	</div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Artemis II Crew Enjoys Visit with Marshall Team Members</strong></h2>



<p><em>By Wayne Smith</em></p>



<p>From talking about continuing the legacy of NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center in space exploration to describing their roles in an upcoming historic mission, Artemis II astronauts enjoyed visiting with center team members Nov. 27.</p>



<p>The crew will be the first to ride aboard NASA’s SLS (Space Launch System) rocket and Orion spacecraft. They will launch atop the rocket to venture around the Moon on Artemis II, the first crewed flight for Artemis. Their mission around the Moon will verify capabilities for humans to explore deep space and pave the way for long-term exploration and science on the lunar surface. Marshall manages the SLS Program.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1404" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="From left, Artemis II astronauts Jeremy Hansen, Christina Koch, and Victor Glover listen as Commander Reid Wiseman talks during an employee event at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center on Nov. 27." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg 3513w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=300,206 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=768,526 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=1024,702 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=1536,1053 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=2048,1404 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=400,274 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=600,411 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=900,617 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=1200,823 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg?resize=2000,1371 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">From left, Artemis II astronauts Jeremy Hansen, Christina Koch, and Victor Glover listen as Commander Reid Wiseman talks during an employee event at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center on Nov. 27. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Charles Beason</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>The four-member crew answered questions from a standing-room only crowd for about an hour inside Activities Building 4316 before taking photos with Marshall team members. The crew consists of NASA astronauts Reid Wiseman, who will be the Artemis II commander, Victor Glover (pilot) and Christina Koch (mission specialist), and Canadian Space Agency astronaut Jeremy Hansen (mission specialist).</p>



<p>They even took the time to send a personalized Christmas greeting to the grandmother of Corey Walker, an atmospheric science programmer at Marshall with Jacobs, who said it would be the perfect gift for her. During the question and answer portion of the event, the astronauts had Walker join them on stage and made a short greeting for his grandmother, Brenda Lowery, who lives on Sand Mountain.</p>



<p>“I can’t wait to give this to her because she loves the space program,” Walker said. “She was young when the astronauts went to the Moon the first time. She has lots of mementos at her house of the space program.”</p>



<p>After acting Center Director Joseph Pelfrey welcomed team members to the event, SLS Program Manager John Honeycutt talked about Marshall’s reputation of excellence in rocket propulsion and the success of Artemis I before introducing the astronauts.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1366" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Glover, third from left, makes a point during the Artemis II crew event with Marshall team members." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=1536,1025 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=2048,1366 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=900,601 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=1200,801 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5627.jpg?resize=2000,1334 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Glover, third from left, makes a point during the Artemis II crew event with Marshall team members. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Charles Beason</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>“Since the beginning, NASA astronauts have launched on historic missions and on rockets designed, developed, and built right here at Marshall Space Flight Center and our Michoud Assembly Facility,” Honeycutt said. “… It seems only fitting that when a new era of human space flight launches on a rocket developed here, that that’s the way it should be. We’ve been entrusted not just with an incredibly powerful and capable rocket, but with the lives of four astronauts. Their safety and return are chief among our responsibilities.”</p>



<p>Wiseman acknowledged Marshall’s rocket excellence, but also pointed out the center’s role in research for future missions to the Moon and working in the lunar environment. The Payload Operations Integration Center at Marshall is the control center for scientific operations on the International Space Station.</p>



<p>“(Marshall) means a lot more to us than getting us off this planet,’ Wiseman said. “It’s also our human research side when we are off the planet. When we are working sustainably in the lunar area, and we see humans on Mars, it’s built on the shoulders of POIC (Payload Operations Integration Center), of human research in orbit. That is the bread and butter of what we’re doing. We’re launching humans and living in space, and that is built right here at Marshall.”</p>



<p>Glover, who will be the first African American on a lunar mission, thanked Marshall team members for their work with SLS and the space station. He spent 168 days in space as a flight engineer aboard the space station for Expedition 64.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1648" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="SLS Program Manager John Honeycutt, left, and acting Center Director Joseph Pelfrey, right, join the Artemis II crew for a photo at the employee event in Activities Building 4316." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=300,241 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=768,618 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=1024,824 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=1536,1236 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=2048,1648 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=400,322 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=600,483 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=900,724 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=1200,965 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5653.jpg?resize=2000,1609 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">SLS Program Manager John Honeycutt, left, and acting Center Director Joseph Pelfrey, right, join the Artemis II crew for a photo at the employee event in Activities Building 4316. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Charles Beason</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>“Thank you for your work supporting our friends who are working on the space station now and for that amazing legacy that we’ve all had the opportunity to be a part of in one facet or another,” Glover said. “We’re here to do the work and be a part of this team. We hope that what we’re doing makes you proud.”</p>



<p>Koch and Hansen also will make history with the Artemis II mission. Koch will be the first woman on a lunar mission, while Hansen will be the first Canadian.</p>



<p>Andy Buehler, a rocket propulsion engineer at Marshall with Boeing, asked Koch what her message to young girls is as they see a female going to the Moon for the first time.</p>



<p>“Surround yourself with people who are encouraging,” Koch said. “Tell yourself you’re going to do great things one day. You can be that voice for yourself. Don’t just strive to be a part of something, strive to be excellent at what you’re doing.”</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1507" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Corey Walker, an atmospheric science programmer at Marshall with Jacobs, smiles with the astronauts as they record a video wishing Walker’s grandmother, Brenda Lowery, merry Christmas. During a question and answer session with the astronauts, Walker asked if he could get a video of them for his grandmother as a Christmas gift for her. Walker said his grandmother loves the space program. At far left is Lance D. Davis, Marshall’s news chief, who served as moderator for the event." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=300,221 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=768,565 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=1024,753 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=1536,1130 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=2048,1507 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=400,294 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=600,442 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=900,662 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=1200,883 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5620.jpg?resize=2000,1472 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Corey Walker, an atmospheric science programmer at Marshall with Jacobs, smiles with the astronauts as they record a video wishing Walker’s grandmother, Brenda Lowery, merry Christmas. During a question and answer session with the astronauts, Walker asked if he could get a video of them for his grandmother as a Christmas gift for her. Walker said his grandmother loves the space program. At far left is Lance D. Davis, Marshall’s news chief, who served as moderator for the event. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Charles Beason</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>Hansen said he is excited about the future of Artemis. He told Marshall team members they are part of something that brings value to the world with NASA’s leadership.</p>



<p>“You’re doing that with partners around the world because you’re choosing to lead,” Hansen said. “We need that kind of leadership and that vision more than ever. We really need to be focused on things that lift up humanity. We have a lot of reason for hope for our future.”</p>



<p><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/feature/our-artemis-crew/#_blank">Learn more</a> about the Artemis II crew.</p>



<p><em>Smith, a Media Fusion employee and the Marshall Star editor, supports the Marshall Office of Communications.</em></p>



<p><strong><strong><a href="#top">› Back to Top</a></strong></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Artemis II Crew Signs NASA Moon Rocket Hardware at Marshall</strong></h2>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1355" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Artemis II Astronauts Victor Glover, Reid Wiseman, Christina Koch, and Jeremy Hansen visit Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, AL on Nov. 27 and sign the Artemis II Orion stage adapter" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=300,198 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=768,508 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=1024,677 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=1536,1016 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=2048,1355 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=400,265 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=600,397 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=900,595 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=1200,794 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5463.jpg?resize=2000,1323 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Brent Gaddes, lead for the Orion stage adapter in the Spacecraft Payload Integration &amp; Evolution Office in the SLS Program at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center, far left, talks with NASA astronauts Reid Wiseman, center, and Christina Koch near the SLS Orion stage adapter for the Artemis II mission during their visit to Marshall on Nov. 27.</div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Charles Beason</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>Artemis II astronauts Victor Glover, Reid Wiseman, and Christina Koch of NASA, and CSA (Canadian Space Agency) astronaut Jeremy Hansen signed the Orion stage adapter for the <a href="http://nasa.gov/sls" rel="noopener">SLS (Space Launch System)</a> rocket at <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers/marshall/home/index.html">NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center</a> on Nov. 27. The hardware is the topmost portion of the SLS rocket that they will launch atop during <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/artemis-ii">Artemis II</a> when the four astronauts inside NASA’s Orion spacecraft will venture around the Moon.</p>



<p>The Orion stage adapter is a small ring structure that connects <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/humans-in-space/orion-spacecraft/">NASA’s Orion spacecraft</a> to the SLS rocket’s <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/exploration/systems/sls/nasa-s-sls-mega-rocket-what-is-the-icps.html">interim cryogenic propulsion stage</a> and fully manufactured at Marshall. At five feet tall and weighing 1,800 pounds, the adapter is the smallest major element of the SLS rocket. During Artemis II, the adapter’s diaphragm will serve as a barrier to prevent gases created during launch from entering the spacecraft.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="3600" height="2400" class="wp-image-571915" style="width: 175px" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg" alt="Artemis II Astronaut Jeremy Hansen visits Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, AL on Nov. 27 and signs the Artemis II Orion stage adapter." srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5666.jpg?resize=2000,1333 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 3600px) 100vw, 3600px" /></a> <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="3600" height="2400" class="wp-image-571918" style="width: 175px" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg" alt="Artemis II Astronaut Christina Koch visits Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, AL on Nov. 27 and signs the Artemis II Orion stage adapter." srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5484.jpg?resize=2000,1333 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 3600px) 100vw, 3600px" /></a> <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="3600" height="2494" class="wp-image-571922" style="width: 175px" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg" alt="Artemis II Astronaut Victor Glover visits Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, AL on Nov. 27 and signs the Artemis II Orion stage adapter." srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=300,208 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=768,532 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=1024,709 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=1536,1064 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=2048,1419 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=400,277 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=600,416 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=900,624 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=1200,831 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5691.jpg?resize=2000,1386 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 3600px) 100vw, 3600px" /></a> <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="3600" height="2525" class="wp-image-571923" style="width: 175px" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg" alt="Artemis II Astronaut Reid Wiseman visits Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, AL on Nov. 27 and signs the Artemis II Orion stage adapter." srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=300,210 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=768,539 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=1024,718 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=1536,1077 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=2048,1436 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=400,281 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=600,421 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=900,631 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=1200,842 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5495.jpg?resize=2000,1403 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 3600px) 100vw, 3600px" /></a><br><em>From left, Artemis II astronauts Jeremy Hansen, Christina Koch, Victor Glover, and Reid Wiseman sign the SLS Orion stage adapter for the Artemis II mission.</em><br><em>NASA/Charles Beason</em></p>



<p>In addition to signing the Orion stage adapter, Wiseman and Koch also visited the Systems Integration Lab at Marshall prior to an employee event.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1412" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Dan Mitchell, lead SLS integrated avionics and software engineer, talks with Wiseman and Koch as they visit the Systems Integration Lab at Marshall." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=300,207 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=768,529 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=1024,706 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=1536,1059 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=2048,1412 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=400,276 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=600,414 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=900,621 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=1200,827 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5420.jpg?resize=2000,1379 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Dan Mitchell, lead SLS integrated avionics and software engineer, talks with Wiseman and Koch as they visit the Systems Integration Lab at Marshall. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Charles Beason</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>NASA is working to land the first woman and first person of color on the Moon under <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/specials/artemis/">Artemis</a>. SLS is part of NASA’s backbone for deep space exploration, along with the Orion spacecraft, advanced spacesuits and rovers, the Gateway in orbit around the Moon, and commercial human landing systems. SLS is the only rocket that can send Orion, astronauts, and supplies to the Moon in a single mission. Through Artemis, NASA will explore more of the lunar surface than ever before and prepare for the next giant leap: sending astronauts to Mars.</p>



<p><strong><strong><a href="#top">› Back to Top</a></strong></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Monthly Brown Bag Seminars Shine Spotlight on Marshall’s Business Units</strong></h2>



<p><em>By Jessica Barnett</em></p>



<p>With thousands of employees across hundreds of departments and teams, there’s no shortage of cool things happening at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center. To help keep Marshall team members up to date, the center recently started a series of monthly brown bag seminars aimed at highlighting its business units.</p>



<p>Each month features a different business unit. On Nov. 7, nearly 300 Marshall team members attended the first seminar, which focused on Marshall’s Moon/Mars Surface Technologies and Systems. In doing so, the participants learned more about the center’s strategy.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1402" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Geologist Jennifer Edmunson, from right, discusses lunar regolith and infrastructure plans during a brown bag seminar Nov. 7 at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center that highlighted the center’s Moon/Mars Surface Technologies and Systems business unit." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=300,205 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=768,526 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=1024,701 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=1536,1052 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=2048,1402 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=400,274 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=600,411 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=900,616 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=1200,822 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2781.jpg?resize=2000,1369 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Geologist Jennifer Edmunson, from right, discusses lunar regolith and infrastructure plans during a brown bag seminar Nov. 7 at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center that highlighted the center’s Moon/Mars Surface Technologies and Systems business unit. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Charles Beason</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>“We’re in between the hopes and dreams of what you might find out there or what the vision of the future on the lunar surface might look like, and what is actually practical,” said Michael Zanetti, a lunar and planetary geologist at Marshall who was also one of the speakers during the Nov. 7 seminar.</p>



<p>Zanetti discussed GPS-denied LiDAR navigation systems, including KNaCK (Kinematic Navigation and Cartography Knapsack), a proof-of-concept 3D terrain mapping, navigation, and algorithm development tool that can be used to determine the layout of portions of the lunar or Martian surface even when there is no light source or GPS to guide it.</p>



<p>He also talked about Marshall’s Lunar Regolith Terrain Facility – a 125-by-125-foot area covered in 500 tons of lunar regolith simulant that can be quickly modified as needed for robotics testing.</p>



<p>“If we’re going to send anything to the lunar surface, we need to make sure that technology is going to be able to function when it gets there,” said Jennifer Edmunson, project manager for Marshall’s Moon-to-Mars Planetary Autonomous Construction Technology Project, or MMPACT. “Testing with regolith is important to do that, but since we don’t have enough regolith material from the Apollo missions, we rely on simulants.”</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1496" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Materials test engineer Annette Gray, far left at table, explains how participants in Marshall’s MERCRII (Metallic Environmentally Resistant Coatings Rapid Innovation Initiative) worked with other centers and NASA partners to develop a radiation-resistant coating to improve the wear resistance of mechanism joints on the lunar or Martian surface." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg 2764w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=300,219 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=768,561 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=1024,748 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=1536,1122 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=2048,1496 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=400,292 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=600,438 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=900,657 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=1200,877 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-2792-edited.jpg?resize=2000,1461 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Materials test engineer Annette Gray, far left at table, explains how participants in Marshall’s MERCRII (Metallic Environmentally Resistant Coatings Rapid Innovation Initiative) worked with other centers and NASA partners to develop a radiation-resistant coating to improve the wear resistance of mechanism joints on the lunar or Martian surface. </div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>MMPACT is currently working to determine how best to build infrastructure on the lunar surface using the regolith and resources already available there. Edmunson shared how the project aims to build landing pads and even habitats on the Moon, but that it’s important to find ways of building that can withstand the extreme temperature variations, lengthy moonquakes, and other challenges that would be faced on the lunar surface.</p>



<p>Joining Edmunson and Zanetti at the seminar was Annette Gray, a materials test engineer who was part of MERCRII (Metallic Environmentally Resistant Coatings Rapid Innovation Initiative). Gray explained how the early career initiative project worked with other centers and NASA partners to develop a radiation-resistant coating to improve the wear resistance of mechanism joints on the lunar or Martian surface.</p>



<p>Part of the initiative included acquiring a Planetary, Lunar, and Asteroid Natural Environment Testbed, or PLANET. Gray said the PLANET was a 2-meter-by-3-meter chamber with up to 1 ton of regolith simulant inside that could test high vacuum, low-density plasma, and various atmospheric conditions.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="942" height="1009" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/brown-bag-attendees.png?w=942" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="Attendees at Marshall’s first brown bag seminar check out lunar regolith samples, view informational displays, and further discuss the featured topics following the seminar." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/brown-bag-attendees.png 942w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/brown-bag-attendees.png?resize=280,300 280w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/brown-bag-attendees.png?resize=768,823 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/brown-bag-attendees.png?resize=373,400 373w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/brown-bag-attendees.png?resize=560,600 560w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/brown-bag-attendees.png?resize=840,900 840w" sizes="(max-width: 942px) 100vw, 942px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Attendees at Marshall’s first brown bag seminar check out lunar regolith samples, view informational displays, and further discuss the featured topics following the seminar.</div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Ray Osorio</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>The seminar ended with a question-and-answer session and a chance for in-person attendees to check out regolith simulant samples.</p>



<p>“It was an excellent way to showcase how the varied work we do at Marshall is enabling future NASA missions and addressing critical gaps,” said MMSTS Strategy Lead Shawn Maynor. “The excitement was palpable, and the discussion was lively. I truly feel that Marshall is in a unique position to capitalize on the evolving space industry.”</p>



<p>The next brown bag seminar is set for January 2024, after the winter holiday season.</p>



<p><em>Barnett, a Media Fusion employee, supports the Marshall Office of Communications.</em></p>



<p><strong><strong><a href="#top">› Back to Top</a></strong></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>NASA Releases Its First International Space Station Tour in Spanish</strong></h2>



<p>Lee esta nota de prensa en español&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/news-release/la-nasa-publica-el-primer-tour-en-espanol-de-la-estacion-espacial/">aquí</a>.</p>



<p>Record-breaking NASA astronaut Frank Rubio provides the agency’s first Spanish-language video tour of humanity’s home in space – the International Space Station.</p>



<p>Rubio welcomes the public aboard the microgravity science laboratory in a behind-the-scenes look at living and working in space recorded during his 371-day mission aboard the space station, the longest single spaceflight in history by an American.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Un tour de la Estación Espacial Internacional con Frank Rubio" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0JU4z-iLmGQ?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The station tour is available to watch on the agency’s&nbsp;<a href="https://plus.nasa.gov/" rel="noopener">NASA+</a>&nbsp;streaming platform,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/connect/apps.html">NASA app</a>, NASA Television,&nbsp;<a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2F%40NASA&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cclaire.a.o%27shea%40nasa.gov%7Ce5a8592aed254e49b53f08dbe18d681e%7C7005d45845be48ae8140d43da96dd17b%7C0%7C0%7C638351769667490197%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=TqApDQ1K1E3ew5y8ZdkLTjQ3EhubhNvJVwdKRHBP%2FW8%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noopener">YouTube</a>, and the agency’s&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/nasatv/">website</a>.</p>



<p>Continuously inhabited for more than 23 years, the space station is a scientific platform where crew members conduct experiments across multiple disciplines of research, including Earth and space science, biology, human physiology, physical sciences, and technology demonstrations that could not be performed on Earth.</p>



<p>The Payload Operations Integration Center at NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center operates, plans, and coordinates the science experiments onboard the space station 365 days a year, 24 hours a day.</p>



<p>The crew living aboard the station are the hands of thousands of researchers on the ground conducting more than 3,300 experiments in microgravity. During his record-breaking mission, Rubio spent many hours contributing to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/research/news/frank-rubio-year-in-space/">scientific activities</a>&nbsp;aboard the orbiting laboratory, conducting everything from human health studies to plant research.</p>



<p>Rubio&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/news-release/record-setting-nasa-astronaut-soon-returns-to-earth-watch-live/">returned</a>&nbsp;to Earth in September, having completed approximately 5,936 orbits of the Earth and a journey of more than 157 million miles during his first spaceflight, roughly the equivalent of 328 trips to the Moon and back.</p>



<p>Get the latest NASA space station news, images and features on&nbsp;<a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Finstagram.com%2Fiss&amp;data=05%7C01%7Ccourtney.m.beasley%40nasa.gov%7Ca428f9e84a2943e8ea8708dba8cf8222%7C7005d45845be48ae8140d43da96dd17b%7C0%7C0%7C638289381411506373%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=0y3PcooHZZxetDf6GH%2FLGTh4Lqy7x2Jmc7mT8%2FXaZ4A%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noopener">Instagram</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fiss&amp;data=05%7C01%7Ccourtney.m.beasley%40nasa.gov%7Ca428f9e84a2943e8ea8708dba8cf8222%7C7005d45845be48ae8140d43da96dd17b%7C0%7C0%7C638289381411506373%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=lRtL8q%2Fszl1GDTBbLBU%2FqiVjJ%2B8erbdyNDjgMwscI6c%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noopener">Facebook</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.twitter.com%2FSpace_Station&amp;data=05%7C01%7Ccourtney.m.beasley%40nasa.gov%7Ca428f9e84a2943e8ea8708dba8cf8222%7C7005d45845be48ae8140d43da96dd17b%7C0%7C0%7C638289381411506373%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=j3rvQYkiGhgtXP1HzWxb55NEQPpMfr6aly%2F6d4Bfkz8%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noopener">X</a>.</p>



<p><strong><strong><a href="#top">› Back to Top</a></strong></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>NASA’s Dragonfly to Proceed with Final Mission Design Work</strong></h2>



<p>NASA’s Dragonfly mission has been authorized to proceed with work on final mission design and fabrication – known as Phase C – during FY (fiscal year) 2024. The agency is postponing formal confirmation of the mission (including its total cost and schedule) until mid-2024, following the release of the FY 2025 President’s Budget Request.</p>



<p>Earlier this year,&nbsp;<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/dragonfly" rel="noopener">Dragonfly</a>&nbsp;– a mission to send a rotorcraft to explore Saturn’s moon Titan –&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/missions/dragonfly/nasas-dragonfly-team-soars-through-major-design-review/">passed all the success criteria</a>&nbsp;of its Preliminary Design Review. The Dragonfly team conducted a re-plan of the mission based on expected funding available in FY 2024 and estimate a revised launch readiness date of July 2028. The agency will officially assess the mission’s launch readiness date in mid-2024 at the agency Program Management Council.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img loading="lazy" width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/new_dragonfly_mission_flying_landing_sequence_animation.gif?w=1280" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="NASA&#039;s Dragonfly rotorcraft-lander animation" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Artist’s impression of Dragonfly heading off toward its next landing spot on Titan.</div><div class="hds-credits">NASA/Johns Hopkins APL/Steve Gribben</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>“The Dragonfly team has successfully overcome a number of technical and programmatic challenges in this daring endeavor to gather new science on Titan,” said Nicola Fox, associate administrator of NASA’s Science Mission Directorate at NASA Headquarters. “I am proud of this team and their ability to keep all aspects of the mission moving toward confirmation.”</p>



<p>Dragonfly takes a novel approach to planetary exploration, for the first time employing a rotorcraft-lander to travel between and sample diverse sites on&nbsp;<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/saturn/moons/titan/" rel="noopener">Titan</a>. Dragonfly’s goal is to characterize the habitability of the moon’s environment, investigate the progression of prebiotic chemistry in an environment where carbon-rich material and liquid water may have mixed for an extended period, and even search for chemical indications of whether water-based or hydrocarbon-based life once existed on Titan.</p>



<p>Dragonfly is being designed and built under the direction of the Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Laboratory in Laurel, Maryland, which manages the mission for NASA. The team includes key partners at NASA’s Goddard Space Flight Center; Lockheed Martin Space in Littleton, Colorado; Sikorsky, a Lockheed Martin company; NASA’s Ames Research Center; NASA’s Langley Research Center; Penn State University in State College, Pennsylvania; Malin Space Science Systems in San Diego, California; Honeybee Robotics in Pasadena, California; NASA’s Jet Propulsion Laboratory; CNES (Centre National d’Etudes Spatiales), the French space agency, in Paris, France; DLR (German Aerospace Center) in Cologne, Germany; and JAXA (Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency) in Tokyo, Japan.</p>



<p>Dragonfly is the fourth mission in NASA’s New Frontiers Program, managed by NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center for the Science Mission Directorate.</p>



<p><strong><strong><a href="#top">› Back to Top</a></strong></strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Webb Telescope: A Prominent Protostar in Perseus</strong></h2>



<p>A new&nbsp;<a href="https://esawebb.org/images/potm/" rel="noopener">Picture of the Month</a>&nbsp;from the NASA/ESA/CSA James Webb Space Telescope reveals intricate details of the Herbig Haro object 797, known as HH 797.</p>



<p>Herbig-Haro objects are luminous regions surrounding newborn stars (known as protostars), and are formed when stellar winds or jets of gas spewing from these newborn stars form shockwaves colliding with nearby gas and dust at high speeds. HH 797, which dominates the lower half of the image, is located close to the young open star cluster IC 348, which is located near the eastern edge of the Perseus dark cloud complex. The bright infrared objects in the upper portion of the image are thought to host two further protostars.</p>


<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-fit "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1984" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="In the lower half of the image is a narrow, horizontal nebula that stretches from edge to edge. It is brightly coloured with more variety on its right side. In the upper half there is a glowing point with multi-coloured light radiating from it in all directions. A bright star with long diffraction spikes lies along the right edge, and a few smaller stars are spread around. The background is covered in a thin haze." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg 4632w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=300,291 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=768,744 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=1024,992 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=1536,1488 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=2048,1984 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=400,388 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=600,581 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=900,872 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=1200,1163 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/webb-esa-potm2311a-4k.jpg?resize=2000,1938 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">The NASA/ESA/CSA James Webb Space Telescope reveals intricate details of the Herbig Haro object 797, or HH 797. HH 797, which dominates the lower half of this image, is located close to the young open star cluster IC 348, which is located near the eastern edge of the Perseus dark cloud complex. The bright infrared objects in the upper portion of the image are thought to host two further protostars. This image was captured with Webb’s Near-InfraRed Camera (NIRCam).</div><div class="hds-credits">ESA/Webb, NASA &amp; CSA, T. Ray (Dublin Institute for Advanced Studies)</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>The image was captured with Webb’s <a href="https://esawebb.org/about/instruments/nircam-niriss/" rel="noopener">NIRCam</a> (Near-InfraRed Camera). Infrared imaging is powerful in studying newborn stars and their outflows, because the youngest stars are invariably still embedded within the gas and dust from which they are formed. The infrared emission of the star’s outflows penetrates the obscuring gas and dust, making Herbig-Haro objects ideal for observation with Webb’s sensitive infrared instruments. Molecules excited by the turbulent conditions, including molecular hydrogen and carbon monoxide, emit infrared light that Webb can collect to visualize the structure of the outflows. NIRCam is particularly good at observing the hot (thousands of degree Celsius) molecules that are excited as a result of shocks.</p>



<p>Using ground-based observations, researchers have previously found that for cold molecular gas associated with HH 797, most of the red-shifted gas (moving away from us) is found to the south (bottom right), while the blue-shifted gas (moving towards us) is to the north (bottom left). A gradient was also found across the outflow, such that at a given distance from the young central star, the velocity of the gas near the eastern edge of the jet is more red-shifted than that of the gas on the western edge. Astronomers in the past thought this was due to the outflow’s rotation. In this higher resolution Webb image, however, we can see that what was thought to be one outflow is in fact made up of two almost parallel outflows with their own separate series of shocks (which explains the velocity asymmetries). The source, located in the small dark region (bottom right of center), and already known from previous observations, is therefore not a single but a double star. Each star is producing its own dramatic outflow. Other outflows are also seen in this image, including one from the protostar in the top right of center along with its illuminated cavity walls.</p>



<p>HH 797 resides directly north of HH 211 (separated by approximately 30 arcseconds), which was the feature of a&nbsp;<a href="https://esawebb.org/news/weic2322/" rel="noopener">Webb image release</a>&nbsp;in September 2023.</p>



<p>The James Webb Space Telescope is the world&#8217;s premier space science observatory. Webb is solving mysteries in our solar system, looking beyond to distant worlds around other stars, and probing the mysterious structures and origins of our universe and our place in it. Webb is an international program led by NASA with its partners, ESA (European Space Agency) and the Canadian Space Agency. Several NASA centers contributed to the project, including&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers/marshall/news/releases/2021/marshall-mirrors-and-mission-history-with-nasas-james-webb-space-telescope.html">NASA’s Marshall Space Flight Center</a>.</p>



<p><strong><strong><a href="#top">› Back to Top</a></strong></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>


            <media:content url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0JU4z-iLmGQ" medium="video"
                width="1280" height="720">
                <media:player url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0JU4z-iLmGQ" />
                <media:title type="plain">Un tour de la Estación Espacial Internacional con Frank
                    Rubio</media:title>
                <media:description type="html"><![CDATA[El astronauta de la NASA Frank Rubio, quien acaba de cumplir una misión récord, es el presentador de un video con el primer tour de la NASA narrado en españo...]]></media:description>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ceb-5632.jpg" />
                <media:rating scheme="urn:simple">nonadult</media:rating>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>NASA Remembers Trailblazing Astronaut, Scientist Mary Cleave</title>
            <link>
                https://www.nasa.gov/news-release/nasa-remembers-trailblazing-astronaut-scientist-mary-cleave/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Abbey A. Donaldson]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 22:30:07 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Former Astronauts]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Astronauts]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nasa.gov/?post_type=press-release&#038;p=572721</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[Retired NASA astronaut Mary Cleave, a veteran of two NASA spaceflights, died Nov. 27. She was 76. A scientist with training in civil and environmental engineering, as well as biological sciences and microbial ecology, Cleave was the first woman to serve as an associate administrator for NASA’s Science Mission Directorate. Born in Southampton, New York, [&#8230;]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1280" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?w=1024" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 46% 14%; object-position: 46% 14%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?resize=240,300 240w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?resize=768,960 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?resize=819,1024 819w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?resize=320,400 320w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?resize=480,600 480w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?resize=720,900 720w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/s85-29954medium.jpg?resize=960,1200 960w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">NASA Astronaut Mary L. Cleave. April 8, 1985</div><div class="hds-credits">NASA </div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>Retired NASA astronaut Mary Cleave, a veteran of two NASA spaceflights, died Nov. 27. She was 76. A scientist with training in civil and environmental engineering, as well as biological sciences and microbial ecology, Cleave was the first woman to serve as an associate administrator for NASA’s Science Mission Directorate.</p>



<p>Born in Southampton, New York, Cleave received a Bachelor of Science degree in biological sciences from Colorado State University, Fort Collins, in 1969, and Master of Science in microbial ecology and a doctorate in civil and environmental engineering, both from Utah State University, Logan, in 1975 and 1979, respectively.</p>



<p>“I’m sad we’ve lost trail blazer Dr. Mary Cleave, shuttle astronaut, veteran of two spaceflights, and first woman to lead the Science Mission Directorate as associate administrator,” said NASA Associate Administrator Bob Cabana. “Mary was a force of nature with a passion for science, exploration, and caring for our home planet. She will be missed.”</p>



<p>Cleave was selected as an astronaut in May 1980. Her technical assignments included flight software verification in the SAIL (Shuttle Avionics Integration Laboratory), spacecraft communicator on five space shuttle flights, and malfunctions procedures book and crew equipment design.</p>



<p>Cleave launched on her first mission, STS-61B, aboard space shuttle Atlantis on Nov. 26,1985. During the flight, the crew deployed communications satellites, conducted two six-hour spacewalks to demonstrate space station construction techniques, operated the Continuous Flow Electrophoresis experiment for McDonnell Douglas and a Getaway Special container for Telesat and tested the Orbiter Experiments Digital Autopilot.</p>



<p>Cleave’s second mission, STS-30, which also was on Atlantis, launched May 4, 1989. It was a four-day flight during which the crew successfully deployed the Magellan Venus exploration spacecraft, the first planetary probe to be deployed from a space shuttle. Magellan arrived at Venus in August 1990 and mapped more than 95% of the surface. In addition, the crew also worked on secondary payloads involving indium crystal growth, electrical storms, and Earth observation studies.</p>



<p>Cleave transferred from NASA’s Johnson Space Center in Houston to the agency’s Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland in May 1991. There, she worked in the Laboratory for Hydrospheric Processes as the project manager for SeaWiFS (Sea-viewing, Wide-Field-of-view-Sensor), an ocean color sensor which monitored vegetation globally.</p>



<p>In March 2000, she went to serve as deputy associate administrator for advanced planning in the Office of Earth Science at NASA’s Headquarters in Washington. From August 2005 to February 2007, Cleave was the associate administrator for NASA’s Science Mission Directorate where she guided an array of research and scientific exploration programs for planet Earth, space weather, the solar system, and the universe. She also oversaw an assortment of grant-based research programs and a diverse constellation of spacecraft, from small, principal investigator-led missions to large flagship missions.</p>



<p>Cleave’s awards included: two NASA Space Flight medals; two NASA Exceptional Service medals; an American Astronautical Society Flight Achievement Award; a NASA Exceptional Achievement Medal; and NASA Engineer of the Year.</p>



<p>Cleave retired from NASA in February 2007.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><a href="https://go.nasa.gov/3uDCykl" rel="noopener"><strong>https://go.nasa.gov/3uDCykl</strong></a></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center">-end-</p>



<p>Cheryl Warner<br>Headquarters, Washington<br>202-358-1600<br><a href="mailto:cheryl.m.warner@nasa.gov">cheryl.m.warner@nasa.gov</a></p>



<p>Courtney Beasley<br>Johnson Space Center, Houston<br>281-483-5111<br><a href="mailto:courtney.m.beasley@nasa.gov">courtney.m.beasley@nasa.gov</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>NASA Tests In-Flight Capability of Artemis Moon Rocket Engine</title>
            <link>
                https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/stennis/nasa-tests-in-flight-capability-of-artemis-moon-rocket-engine/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[LaToya Dean]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 22:11:37 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Stennis Space Center]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Space Launch System (SLS)]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nasa.gov/?p=572971</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[NASA conducted the third RS-25 engine hot fire in a critical 12-test certification series Nov. 29, demonstrating a key capability necessary for flight of the SLS (Space Launch System) rocket during Artemis missions to the Moon and beyond. NASA is conducting the series of tests to certify new manufacturing processes for producing RS-25 engines for [&#8230;]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="padding-top-5 padding-bottom-3 width-full maxw-full hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-article-intro"><div class="width-full maxw-full article-header"><div class="margin-bottom-2 width-full maxw-full"><p class="label carbon-60 margin-0 margin-bottom-3 padding-0">2 min read</p><h1 class="display-48 margin-bottom-2">Preparations for Next Moonwalk Simulations Underway (and Underwater)</h1></div></div></div>

<div id="" class="hds-image-carousel grid-container grid-container-block padding-top-8 padding-bottom-8 hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-image-carousel">		<div class="hds-carousel-wrapper">
			<div class="image-carousel-slider margin-0" id="image-carousel-slider">
											<div class="display-block width-full">
							<figure class="margin-0">
								<div class="hds-cover-wrapper hds-image-carousel-slide margin-bottom-2">
								<div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img loading="lazy" width="640" height="427" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="RS-25 Engine Test" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg 5568w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03233h.jpg?resize=2000,1333 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">NASA completed a full duration, 650-second hot fire of the RS-25 certification engine Nov. 29, continuing a critical test series to support future SLS (Space Launch System) missions to deep space as NASA explores the secrets of the universe for the benefit of all. </div><div class="hds-credits">Danny Nowlin</div></figcaption></div>								</div>
							</figure>
						</div>
											<div class="display-block width-full">
							<figure class="margin-0">
								<div class="hds-cover-wrapper hds-image-carousel-slide margin-bottom-2">
								<div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img loading="lazy" width="640" height="426" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="close up engine test on RS-25 Engine" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.02); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg 5550w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=300,199 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=768,511 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=1024,681 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=1536,1021 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=2048,1362 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=400,266 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=600,399 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=900,598 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=1200,798 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03229h.jpg?resize=2000,1330 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">NASA completed a full duration, 650-second hot fire of the RS-25 certification engine Nov. 29, continuing a critical test series to support future SLS (Space Launch System) missions to deep space as NASA explores the secrets of the universe for the benefit of all. </div><div class="hds-credits">Danny Nowlin</div></figcaption></div>								</div>
							</figure>
						</div>
											<div class="display-block width-full">
							<figure class="margin-0">
								<div class="hds-cover-wrapper hds-image-carousel-slide margin-bottom-2">
								<div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img loading="lazy" width="640" height="426" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Vapor clouds erupt from a RS-25 Engine during testing" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg 5550w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=300,199 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=768,511 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=1024,681 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=1536,1021 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=2048,1362 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=400,266 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=600,399 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=900,598 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=1200,798 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ssc-20231129-s03226h.jpg?resize=2000,1330 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">NASA completed a full duration, 650-second hot fire of the RS-25 certification engine Nov. 29, continuing a critical test series to support future SLS (Space Launch System) missions to deep space as NASA explores the secrets of the universe for the benefit of all. </div><div class="hds-credits">Danny Nowlin</div></figcaption></div>								</div>
							</figure>
						</div>
								</div>
			<div class="hds-carousel-nav display-flex margin-left-auto margin-right-0">
				<button class="hds-carousel-nav-arrow hds-carousel-arrow-prev">
					<svg version="1.1" x="0px" y="0px" width="9px" height="9px" viewBox="0 0 9 9"><path class="st0" d="M3.5,4.5l3.7-3.6L6.3,0L1.8,4.5L6.3,9l0.9-0.9L3.5,4.5z"></path></svg>
				</button>
				<button class="hds-carousel-nav-arrow hds-carousel-arrow-next margin-right-0">
					<svg version="1.1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" x="0px" y="0px" width="9px" height="9px" viewBox="0 0 9 9"><path class="st0" d="M5.5,4.5L1.8,8.1L2.7,9l4.5-4.5L2.7,0L1.8,0.9L5.5,4.5z"></path></svg>
				</button>
			</div>
		</div>
		</div>


<p>NASA conducted the third RS-25 engine hot fire in a critical 12-test certification series Nov. 29, demonstrating a key capability necessary for flight of the <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/humans-in-space/space-launch-system/">SLS</a> (Space Launch System) rocket during Artemis missions to the Moon and beyond.</p>



<p>NASA is conducting the series of tests to certify new manufacturing processes for producing RS-25 engines for future deep space missions, beginning with Artemis V. Aerojet Rocketdyne, an L3Harris Technologies Company and lead engines contractor for the SLS rocket, is incorporating new manufacturing techniques and processes, such as 3D printing, in production of new RS-25 engines.</p>



<p>Crews gimbaled, or pivoted, the <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/sls_rs25_engine_fs_508.pdf">RS-25</a> engine around a central point during the almost 11-minute (650 seconds) hot fire on the Fred Haise Test Stand at NASA’s Stennis Space Center near Bay St. Louis, Mississippi. The gimbaling technique is used to control and stabilize SLS as it reaches orbit.</p>



<p>During the Nov. 29 test, operators also pushed the engine beyond any parameters it might experience during flight to provide a margin of operational safety. The 650-second test exceeded the 500 seconds RS-25 engines must operate to help power SLS to space. The RS-25 engine also was fired to 113% power level, exceeding the 111% level needed to lift SLS to orbit.<em></em></p>



<p>The ongoing series will stretch into 2024 as NASA continues its mission to return humans to the lunar surface to establish a long-term presence for scientific discovery and to prepare for human missions to Mars.</p>



<p>Four RS-25 engines fire simultaneously to generate a combined 1.6 million pounds of thrust at launch and 2 million pounds of thrust during ascent to help power each SLS flight. NASA and Aerojet Rocketdyne modified 16 holdover space shuttle main engines, all proven flightworthy at NASA Stennis, for Artemis missions I through IV.</p>



<p>Every new RS-25 engine that will help power SLS also will be tested at NASA Stennis. RS-25 tests at the site are conducted by a combined team of NASA, Aerojet Rocketdyne, and Syncom Space Services operators. Syncom Space Services is the prime contractor for <a href="http://www.nasa.gov/centers/stennis/">Stennis</a> facilities and operations.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Social Media</h2>



<p>Stay connected with the mission on social media, and let people know you&#8217;re following it on X, Facebook, and Instagram using the hashtags #Artemis, #NASAStennis, #SLS. Follow and tag these accounts:</p>


<div id="" class="hds-social-media hds-social-media--horizontal grid-container grid-container-block nasa-gb-align-center width-full maxw-full margin-y-0 padding-y-5 padding-x-3 desktop:padding-x-0 font-weight-bold hds-module aligncenter wp-block-nasa-blocks-social-media-links">		<div class="display-flex flex-align-center padding-y-1" id="social-facebook">
			<div class="circle-4 minw-4 display-flex flex-align-center flex-justify-center" style="background-color: #4267B2;">
				<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" aria-labelledby="facebookIconTitle"><title id="facebookIconTitle">Facebook logo</title><path d="M9 8h-3v4h3v12h5v-12h3.642l.358-4h-4v-1.667c0-.955.192-1.333 1.115-1.333h2.885v-5h-3.808c-3.596 0-5.192 1.583-5.192 4.615v3.385z"/></svg>			</div>
			<div class="hds-social-media-items padding-left-2">
				<a target="_blank" class="margin-right-2" href="https://facebook.com/NASAStennis" aria-label="Go to @NASAStennis on facebook" rel="noopener">@NASAStennis</a>			</div>
		</div>
				<div class="display-flex flex-align-center padding-y-1" id="social-twitter">
			<div class="circle-4 minw-4 display-flex flex-align-center flex-justify-center" style="background-color: #1DA1F2;">
				<svg width="1200" height="1227" viewBox="0 0 1200 1227" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M714.163 519.284L1160.89 0H1055.03L667.137 450.887L357.328 0H0L468.492 681.821L0 1226.37H105.866L515.491 750.218L842.672 1226.37H1200L714.137 519.284H714.163ZM569.165 687.828L521.697 619.934L144.011 79.6944H306.615L611.412 515.685L658.88 583.579L1055.08 1150.3H892.476L569.165 687.854V687.828Z" fill="white"/></svg>			</div>
			<div class="hds-social-media-items padding-left-2">
				<a target="_blank" class="margin-right-2" href="https://x.com/NASAStennis" aria-label="Go to @NASAStennis on twitter">@NASAStennis</a>			</div>
		</div>
				<div class="display-flex flex-align-center padding-y-1" id="social-instagram">
			<div class="circle-4 minw-4 display-flex flex-align-center flex-justify-center" style="background-color: #833AB4;">
				<svg version="1.1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" width="169.063px" height="169.063px" viewBox="0 0 169.063 169.063" style="enable-background:new 0 0 169.063 169.063;" xml:space="preserve" aria-labelledby="instagramIconTitle"><title id="instagramIconTitle">Instagram logo</title><g> <path d="M122.406,0H46.654C20.929,0,0,20.93,0,46.655v75.752c0,25.726,20.929,46.655,46.654,46.655h75.752 c25.727,0,46.656-20.93,46.656-46.655V46.655C169.063,20.93,148.133,0,122.406,0z M154.063,122.407 c0,17.455-14.201,31.655-31.656,31.655H46.654C29.2,154.063,15,139.862,15,122.407V46.655C15,29.201,29.2,15,46.654,15h75.752 c17.455,0,31.656,14.201,31.656,31.655V122.407z"/> <path d="M84.531,40.97c-24.021,0-43.563,19.542-43.563,43.563c0,24.02,19.542,43.561,43.563,43.561s43.563-19.541,43.563-43.561 C128.094,60.512,108.552,40.97,84.531,40.97z M84.531,113.093c-15.749,0-28.563-12.812-28.563-28.561 c0-15.75,12.813-28.563,28.563-28.563s28.563,12.813,28.563,28.563C113.094,100.281,100.28,113.093,84.531,113.093z"/> <path d="M129.921,28.251c-2.89,0-5.729,1.17-7.77,3.22c-2.051,2.04-3.23,4.88-3.23,7.78c0,2.891,1.18,5.73,3.23,7.78 c2.04,2.04,4.88,3.22,7.77,3.22c2.9,0,5.73-1.18,7.78-3.22c2.05-2.05,3.22-4.89,3.22-7.78c0-2.9-1.17-5.74-3.22-7.78 C135.661,29.421,132.821,28.251,129.921,28.251z"/></g></svg>			</div>
			<div class="hds-social-media-items padding-left-2">
				<a target="_blank" class="margin-right-2" href="https://instagram.com/NASAStennis" aria-label="Go to @NASAStennis on instagram" rel="noopener">@NASAStennis</a>			</div>
		</div>
		</div>

<div id="" class="nasa-gb-align-full width-full maxw-full padding-x-3 padding-y-0 hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-credits-and-details">
<section class="padding-x-0 padding-top-5 padding-bottom-2 desktop:padding-top-7 desktop:padding-bottom-9">
	<div class="grid-row grid-container maxw-widescreen padding-0">
		<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-2 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
			<div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black">
				<div class="margin-bottom-2">
					<h2 class="heading-14">Share</h2>
				</div>
				<div class="padding-bottom-2">
					<ul class="social-icons social-icons-round">
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-x">
							<a href="https://x.com/intent/tweet?via=NASA&#038;text=NASA%20Tests%20In-Flight%20Capability%20of%20Artemis%20Moon%20Rocket%20Engine&#038;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nasa.gov%2Fcenters-and-facilities%2Fstennis%2Fnasa-tests-in-flight-capability-of-artemis-moon-rocket-engine%2F" aria-label="Share on X.">
								<svg width="1200" height="1227" viewBox="0 0 1200 1227" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M714.163 519.284L1160.89 0H1055.03L667.137 450.887L357.328 0H0L468.492 681.821L0 1226.37H105.866L515.491 750.218L842.672 1226.37H1200L714.137 519.284H714.163ZM569.165 687.828L521.697 619.934L144.011 79.6944H306.615L611.412 515.685L658.88 583.579L1055.08 1150.3H892.476L569.165 687.854V687.828Z" fill="white"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-facebook">
							<a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nasa.gov%2Fcenters-and-facilities%2Fstennis%2Fnasa-tests-in-flight-capability-of-artemis-moon-rocket-engine%2F" aria-label="Share on Facebook.">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M9 8h-3v4h3v12h5v-12h3.642l.358-4h-4v-1.667c0-.955.192-1.333 1.115-1.333h2.885v-5h-3.808c-3.596 0-5.192 1.583-5.192 4.615v3.385z"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-linkedin">
							<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/shareArticle?mini=true&#038;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nasa.gov%2Fcenters-and-facilities%2Fstennis%2Fnasa-tests-in-flight-capability-of-artemis-moon-rocket-engine%2F" aria-label="Share on LinkedIn.">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M4.98 3.5c0 1.381-1.11 2.5-2.48 2.5s-2.48-1.119-2.48-2.5c0-1.38 1.11-2.5 2.48-2.5s2.48 1.12 2.48 2.5zm.02 4.5h-5v16h5v-16zm7.982 0h-4.968v16h4.969v-8.399c0-4.67 6.029-5.052 6.029 0v8.399h4.988v-10.131c0-7.88-8.922-7.593-11.018-3.714v-2.155z"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-rss">
							<a href="/feed/" aria-label="Subscribe to RSS feed.">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 800 800" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M493 652H392c0-134-111-244-244-244V307c189 0 345 156 345 345zm71 0c0-228-188-416-416-416V132c285 0 520 235 520 520z"/><circle cx="219" cy="581" r="71"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
					</ul>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
			<div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black">
				<div class="margin-bottom-2">
					<h2 class="heading-14">Details</h2>
				</div>
				<div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3">
					<div class="grid-col-4">
						<div class="subheading">Last Updated</div>
					</div>
					<div class="grid-col-8">Nov 29, 2023</div>
				</div>
			<div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3"><div class="grid-col-4"><div class="subheading">Editor</div></div><div class="grid-col-8">NASA Stennis Communications</div></div><div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3"><div class="grid-col-4"><div class="subheading">Contact</div></div><div class="grid-col-8"><div class="margin-bottom-3"><div>C. Lacy Thompson</div><div><a href="mailto:cal&#118;&#105;&#110;.l&#46;t&#104;&#111;&#109;&#112;son&#64;&#110;&#97;sa.go&#118;">c&#97;&#108;v&#105;&#110;.&#108;.t&#104;o&#109;p&#115;&#111;n&#64;&#110;a&#115;&#97;.&#103;&#111;&#118;</a> / (228) 688-3333</div></div></div></div><div class="grid-row"><div class="grid-col-4"><div class="subheading">Location</div></div><div class="grid-col-8">Stennis Space Center</div></div>			</div>
		</div>
	<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0"><div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black "><div class="margin-bottom-2"><h2 class="heading-14">Related Terms</h2></div><ul class="article-tags"><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/stennis-space-center/">Stennis Space Center</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/directorates/esdmd/common-exploration-systems-development-division/space-launch-system/">Space Launch System (SLS)</a></li></ul></div></div>
	</div>
</section>
	</div>

<div id="" class="nasa-gb-align-full width-full maxw-full padding-x-3 padding-y-0 hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-related-articles">		<section class="hds-related-articles padding-x-0 padding-y-3 desktop:padding-top-7 desktop:padding-bottom-9">
			<div class="w-100 grid-row grid-container maxw-widescreen padding-0 text-align-left">
				<div class="margin-bottom-4"><h2 style="max-width: 100%;" class="width-full w-full maxw-full">Explore More</h2></div>
			</div>
			<div class="grid-row grid-container maxw-widescreen padding-0">
										<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-4 margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0 desktop:padding-right-3">
						<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/stennis/nasa-to-highlight-inclusion-during-bayou-classic-event/" class="color-carbon-black">
							<div class="margin-bottom-2">
								<div class="hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black minh-mobile">
								<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="300" height="169" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/nasa_meatball_1_2.jpeg?w=300" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/nasa_meatball_1_2.jpeg 985w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/nasa_meatball_1_2.jpeg?resize=300,169 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/nasa_meatball_1_2.jpeg?resize=768,432 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/nasa_meatball_1_2.jpeg?resize=400,225 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/nasa_meatball_1_2.jpeg?resize=600,337 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/nasa_meatball_1_2.jpeg?resize=900,506 900w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>								</div>
							</div>
							<div class="padding-right-0 desktop:padding-right-10">
								<div class="subheading margin-bottom-1">3 min read</div>
								<div class="margin-bottom-1"><h3 class="related-article-title">NASA to Highlight Inclusion During Bayou Classic Event </h3></div>
																<div class="display-flex flex-align-center label related-article-label margin-bottom-1 color-carbon-60">
									<span class="display-flex flex-align-center margin-right-2">
										<svg version="1.1" class="square-2 margin-right-1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" width="16px" height="16px" viewBox="0 0 16 16" style="enable-background:new 0 0 16 16;" xml:space="preserve"><g><g><path d="M8,0C3.5,0-0.1,3.7,0,8.2C0.1,12.5,3.6,16,8,16c4.4,0,8-3.6,8-8C16,3.5,12.4,0,8,0z M8,15.2 C4,15.2,0.8,12,0.8,8C0.8,4,4,0.8,8,0.8c3.9,0,7.2,3.2,7.2,7.1C15.2,11.9,12,15.2,8,15.2z"/><path d="M5.6,12c0.8-0.8,1.6-1.6,2.4-2.4c0.8,0.8,1.6,1.6,2.4,2.4c0-2.7,0-5.3,0-8C8.8,4,7.2,4,5.6,4 C5.6,6.7,5.6,9.3,5.6,12z"/></g></g></svg>
										<span>Article</span>
									</span>
									<span class="">
										1 week ago									</span>
								</div>
							</div>
						</a>
					</div>
									<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-4 margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0 desktop:padding-right-3">
						<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/directorates/stmd/stmd-prizes-challenges-crowdsourcing-program/centennial-challenges/cube-quest-concludes-wins-lessons-learned-from-centennial-challenge/" class="color-carbon-black">
							<div class="margin-bottom-2">
								<div class="hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black minh-mobile">
								<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1920" height="1280" src="https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=1920&amp;h=1280&amp;fit=clip&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=1920&amp;h=1280&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 1920w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=300&amp;h=200&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 300w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=768&amp;h=512&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 768w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=683&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 1024w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=1536&amp;h=1024&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 1536w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=400&amp;h=267&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 400w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 600w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=900&amp;h=600&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 900w, https://images-assets.nasa.gov/image/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009/KSC-20210805-PH-CSH01_0009~large.jpg?w=1200&amp;h=800&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cfocalpoint 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></figure>								</div>
							</div>
							<div class="padding-right-0 desktop:padding-right-10">
								<div class="subheading margin-bottom-1">5 min read</div>
								<div class="margin-bottom-1"><h3 class="related-article-title">Cube Quest Concludes: Wins, Lessons Learned from Centennial Challenge</h3></div>
																<div class="display-flex flex-align-center label related-article-label margin-bottom-1 color-carbon-60">
									<span class="display-flex flex-align-center margin-right-2">
										<svg version="1.1" class="square-2 margin-right-1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" width="16px" height="16px" viewBox="0 0 16 16" style="enable-background:new 0 0 16 16;" xml:space="preserve"><g><g><path d="M8,0C3.5,0-0.1,3.7,0,8.2C0.1,12.5,3.6,16,8,16c4.4,0,8-3.6,8-8C16,3.5,12.4,0,8,0z M8,15.2 C4,15.2,0.8,12,0.8,8C0.8,4,4,0.8,8,0.8c3.9,0,7.2,3.2,7.2,7.1C15.2,11.9,12,15.2,8,15.2z"/><path d="M5.6,12c0.8-0.8,1.6-1.6,2.4-2.4c0.8,0.8,1.6,1.6,2.4,2.4c0-2.7,0-5.3,0-8C8.8,4,7.2,4,5.6,4 C5.6,6.7,5.6,9.3,5.6,12z"/></g></g></svg>
										<span>Article</span>
									</span>
									<span class="">
										2 weeks ago									</span>
								</div>
							</div>
						</a>
					</div>
									<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-4 margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0 desktop:padding-right-3">
						<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/centers-and-facilities/stennis/november-lagniappe-2023/" class="color-carbon-black">
							<div class="margin-bottom-2">
								<div class="hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black minh-mobile">
								<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="300" height="200" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?w=300" class="attachment-medium size-medium" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg 3600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/dsc-5193.jpg?resize=2000,1333 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>								</div>
							</div>
							<div class="padding-right-0 desktop:padding-right-10">
								<div class="subheading margin-bottom-1">9 min read</div>
								<div class="margin-bottom-1"><h3 class="related-article-title">Lagniappe</h3></div>
																<div class="display-flex flex-align-center label related-article-label margin-bottom-1 color-carbon-60">
									<span class="display-flex flex-align-center margin-right-2">
										<svg version="1.1" class="square-2 margin-right-1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" width="16px" height="16px" viewBox="0 0 16 16" style="enable-background:new 0 0 16 16;" xml:space="preserve"><g><g><path d="M8,0C3.5,0-0.1,3.7,0,8.2C0.1,12.5,3.6,16,8,16c4.4,0,8-3.6,8-8C16,3.5,12.4,0,8,0z M8,15.2 C4,15.2,0.8,12,0.8,8C0.8,4,4,0.8,8,0.8c3.9,0,7.2,3.2,7.2,7.1C15.2,11.9,12,15.2,8,15.2z"/><path d="M5.6,12c0.8-0.8,1.6-1.6,2.4-2.4c0.8,0.8,1.6,1.6,2.4,2.4c0-2.7,0-5.3,0-8C8.8,4,7.2,4,5.6,4 C5.6,6.7,5.6,9.3,5.6,12z"/></g></g></svg>
										<span>Article</span>
									</span>
									<span class="">
										2 weeks ago									</span>
								</div>
							</div>
						</a>
					</div>
							</div>
		</section>
		</div>

<div id="" class="hds-topic-cards nasa-gb-align-full maxw-full width-full padding-y-6 padding-x-3 color-mode-dark hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-topic-cards">		<div class="grid-container grid-container-block-lg padding-x-0">
			<div class="grid-row flex-align-center margin-bottom-3">
				<div class="desktop:grid-col-8 margin-bottom-2 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
					<div class="label color-carbon-60 margin-bottom-2">Keep Exploring</div>
					<h2 class="heading-36 line-height-sm">Discover More Topics from NASA Stennis</h2>
				</div>
			</div>
				<div class="grid-row grid-gap-2 hds-topic-cards-wrapper">
					<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/stennis/doing-business-with-stennis/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<p class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Doing Business with NASA Stennis</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1536" height="1022" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?w=1536" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg 4256w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=768,511 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=1024,681 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=1536,1022 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=2048,1363 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=400,266 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=600,399 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=900,599 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=1200,798 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ssc-2012-01000-full.jpg?resize=2000,1331 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1536px) 100vw, 1536px" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/stennis/about-stennis/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<p class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>About NASA Stennis</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="879" height="485" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ssc-20180630-s01138h.jpg?w=879" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ssc-20180630-s01138h.jpg 879w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ssc-20180630-s01138h.jpg?resize=300,166 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ssc-20180630-s01138h.jpg?resize=768,424 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ssc-20180630-s01138h.jpg?resize=400,221 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/ssc-20180630-s01138h.jpg?resize=600,331 600w" sizes="(max-width: 879px) 100vw, 879px" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/stennis/visit-stennis/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<p class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Visit NASA Stennis</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1536" height="1024" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?w=1536" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg 2560w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=2048,1366 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=900,600 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/infinity-walk.jpeg?resize=2000,1334 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1536px) 100vw, 1536px" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://www.nasa.gov/stennis/media-resources/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<p class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>NASA Stennis Media Resources</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1536" height="1020" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?w=1536" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg 2784w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=300,199 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=768,510 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=1024,680 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=1536,1020 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=2048,1359 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=400,266 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=600,398 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=900,597 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=1200,797 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/ssc-2010-02732h_-_general.jpg?resize=2000,1328 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1536px) 100vw, 1536px" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>NASA’s Hubble Space Telescope Pauses Science Due to Gyro Issue</title>
            <link>
                https://science.nasa.gov/missions/hubble/nasas-hubble-space-telescope-pauses-science-due-to-gyro-issue/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 21:30:14 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Astrophysics]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Astrophysics Division]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Goddard Space Flight Center]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Hubble Space Telescope]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Science Mission Directorate]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">
                https://science.nasa.gov/missions/hubble/nasas-hubble-space-telescope-pauses-science-due-to-gyro-issue/</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[NASA is working to resume science operations of the agency’s Hubble Space Telescope after it entered safe mode Nov. 23 due to an ongoing gyroscope (gyro) issue. Hubble’s instruments are stable, and the telescope is in good health. The telescope automatically entered safe mode when one of its three gyroscopes gave faulty readings. The gyros […]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="padding-top-5 padding-bottom-3 width-full maxw-full hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-article-intro"> 

	<div class="width-full maxw-full article-header">
		<div class="margin-bottom-2 width-full maxw-full">
			<p class="label carbon-60 margin-0 margin-bottom-3 padding-0">2 min read</p>
			<h1 class="display-48 margin-bottom-2">NASA’s Hubble Space Telescope Pauses Science Due to Gyro Issue</h1>
		</div>	
	</div>

	</div>

<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img fetchpriority="high" width="2048" height="1399" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048 not-transparent" alt="Hubble, at top center, against the black background of space. Earth limb is visible in the lower-left corner." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 61% 28%; object-position: 61% 28%; object-fit: cover;--dominant-color: #3f4142;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg 4288w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=300,205 300w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=768,525 768w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=1024,699 1024w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=1536,1049 1536w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=2048,1399 2048w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=400,273 400w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=600,410 600w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=900,615 900w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=1200,820 1200w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hubble-in-orbit-s125e011844-1.jpg?resize=2000,1366 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" loading="eager" data-has-transparency="false" data-dominant-color="3f4142" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-caption-text p-sm margin-0">Hubble orbiting more than 300 miles above Earth as seen from the space shuttle. </div><div class="hds-credits">NASA</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>NASA is working to resume science operations of the agency’s <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble/" rel="noopener">Hubble Space Telescope</a> after it entered safe mode Nov. 23 due to an ongoing gyroscope (gyro) issue. Hubble’s <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble/observatory/design/instruments/" rel="noopener">instruments</a> are stable, and the telescope is in good health.</p>



<p>The telescope automatically entered safe mode when one of its three gyroscopes gave faulty readings. The gyros measure the telescope’s turn rates and are part of the system that determines which <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble/observatory/design/pointing-control/" rel="noopener">direction the telescope is pointed</a>. While in safe mode, science operations are suspended, and the telescope waits for new directions from the ground.</p>



<p>Hubble first went into safe mode Nov. 19. Although the operations team successfully recovered the spacecraft to resume observations the following day, the unstable gyro caused the observatory to suspend science operations once again Nov. 21. Following a successful recovery, Hubble entered safe mode again Nov. 23.</p>



<p>The team is now running tests to characterize the issue and develop solutions. If necessary, the spacecraft can be re-configured to operate with <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble/observatory/design/hubble-one-gyro-mode/" rel="noopener">only one gyro</a>. The spacecraft had six new gyros installed during the <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble/observatory/missions-to-hubble/servicing-mission-4/" rel="noopener">fifth and final space shuttle servicing mission in 2009</a>. To date, three of those gyros remain operational, including the gyro currently experiencing fluctuations. Hubble uses three gyros to maximize efficiency, but could continue to make science observations with only one gyro if required.</p>



<p>NASA anticipates Hubble will continue making groundbreaking discoveries, working with other observatories, such as the agency’s <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/webb/" rel="noopener">James Webb Space Telescope</a>, throughout this decade and possibly into the next.</p>



<p>Launched in 1990, Hubble has been observing the universe for more than 33 years. Read more about some of <a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble/science/science-highlights/" rel="noopener">Hubble’s greatest scientific discoveries</a>.</p>



<p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline">Media Contacts</span>:</em></strong></p>



<p><strong><em>Claire Andreoli</em></strong><br><strong><em>NASA’s </em></strong><a href="http://www.nasa.gov/goddard"><strong><em>Goddard Space Flight Center</em></strong></a>, <strong><em>Greenbelt, MD</em></strong><br><a href="mailto:claire.andreoli@nasa.gov" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong><em>claire.andreoli@nasa.gov</em></strong></a></p>



<p><strong><em>Alise Fisher<br>NASA <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/">Headquarters</a>, Washington, D.C.<br><a href="mailto:alise.m.fisher@nasa.gov">alise.m.fisher@nasa.gov</a></em></strong></p>


<div id="" class="nasa-gb-align-full width-full maxw-full padding-x-3 padding-y-0 article_a hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-credits-and-details">	<!-- This should be a block -->
	<section class="padding-x-0 padding-top-5 padding-bottom-2 desktop:padding-top-7 desktop:padding-bottom-9">
	<div class="grid-row grid-container maxw-widescreen padding-0">
		<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-2 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
			<div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black">
				<div class="margin-bottom-2"><h2 class="heading-14">Share</h2></div>
				<div class="padding-bottom-2">
					<ul class="social-icons social-icons-round">
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-twitter  social-icon-x">
							<a href="https://x.com" aria-label="Link to X.">
							<svg width="1200" height="1227" viewBox="0 0 1200 1227" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path d="M714.163 519.284L1160.89 0H1055.03L667.137 450.887L357.328 0H0L468.492 681.821L0 1226.37H105.866L515.491 750.218L842.672 1226.37H1200L714.137 519.284H714.163ZM569.165 687.828L521.697 619.934L144.011 79.6944H306.615L611.412 515.685L658.88 583.579L1055.08 1150.3H892.476L569.165 687.854V687.828Z" fill="white"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-facebook">
							<a href="https://facebook.com" aria-label="Link to Facebook." rel="noopener">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M9 8h-3v4h3v12h5v-12h3.642l.358-4h-4v-1.667c0-.955.192-1.333 1.115-1.333h2.885v-5h-3.808c-3.596 0-5.192 1.583-5.192 4.615v3.385z"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-linkedin">
							<a href="https://linkedin.com" aria-label="Link to LinkedIn." rel="noopener">
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" aria-hidden="true"><path d="M4.98 3.5c0 1.381-1.11 2.5-2.48 2.5s-2.48-1.119-2.48-2.5c0-1.38 1.11-2.5 2.48-2.5s2.48 1.12 2.48 2.5zm.02 4.5h-5v16h5v-16zm7.982 0h-4.968v16h4.969v-8.399c0-4.67 6.029-5.052 6.029 0v8.399h4.988v-10.131c0-7.88-8.922-7.593-11.018-3.714v-2.155z"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
						<li class="social-icon social-icon-share">
							<a href="https://rss.com" aria-label="Link to RSS." rel="noopener">
								<svg height="512pt" viewBox="-21 0 512 512" width="512pt" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" aria-hidden="true"><path d="m453.332031 85.332031c0 38.292969-31.039062 69.335938-69.332031 69.335938s-69.332031-31.042969-69.332031-69.335938c0-38.289062 31.039062-69.332031 69.332031-69.332031s69.332031 31.042969 69.332031 69.332031zm0 0"/><path d="m384 170.667969c-47.0625 0-85.332031-38.273438-85.332031-85.335938 0-47.058593 38.269531-85.332031 85.332031-85.332031s85.332031 38.273438 85.332031 85.332031c0 47.0625-38.269531 85.335938-85.332031 85.335938zm0-138.667969c-29.417969 0-53.332031 23.9375-53.332031 53.332031 0 29.398438 23.914062 53.335938 53.332031 53.335938s53.332031-23.9375 53.332031-53.335938c0-29.394531-23.914062-53.332031-53.332031-53.332031zm0 0"/><path d="m453.332031 426.667969c0 38.289062-31.039062 69.332031-69.332031 69.332031s-69.332031-31.042969-69.332031-69.332031c0-38.292969 31.039062-69.335938 69.332031-69.335938s69.332031 31.042969 69.332031 69.335938zm0 0"/><path d="m384 512c-47.0625 0-85.332031-38.273438-85.332031-85.332031 0-47.0625 38.269531-85.335938 85.332031-85.335938s85.332031 38.273438 85.332031 85.335938c0 47.058593-38.269531 85.332031-85.332031 85.332031zm0-138.667969c-29.417969 0-53.332031 23.9375-53.332031 53.335938 0 29.394531 23.914062 53.332031 53.332031 53.332031s53.332031-23.9375 53.332031-53.332031c0-29.398438-23.914062-53.335938-53.332031-53.335938zm0 0"/><path d="m154.667969 256c0 38.292969-31.042969 69.332031-69.335938 69.332031-38.289062 0-69.332031-31.039062-69.332031-69.332031s31.042969-69.332031 69.332031-69.332031c38.292969 0 69.335938 31.039062 69.335938 69.332031zm0 0"/><path d="m85.332031 341.332031c-47.058593 0-85.332031-38.269531-85.332031-85.332031s38.273438-85.332031 85.332031-85.332031c47.0625 0 85.335938 38.269531 85.335938 85.332031s-38.273438 85.332031-85.335938 85.332031zm0-138.664062c-29.417969 0-53.332031 23.933593-53.332031 53.332031s23.914062 53.332031 53.332031 53.332031c29.421875 0 53.335938-23.933593 53.335938-53.332031s-23.914063-53.332031-53.335938-53.332031zm0 0"/><path d="m135.703125 245.761719c-7.425781 0-14.636719-3.863281-18.5625-10.773438-5.824219-10.21875-2.238281-23.253906 7.980469-29.101562l197.949218-112.851563c10.21875-5.867187 23.253907-2.28125 29.101563 7.976563 5.824219 10.21875 2.238281 23.253906-7.980469 29.101562l-197.953125 112.851563c-3.328125 1.898437-6.953125 2.796875-10.535156 2.796875zm0 0"/><path d="m333.632812 421.761719c-3.585937 0-7.210937-.898438-10.539062-2.796875l-197.953125-112.851563c-10.21875-5.824219-13.800781-18.859375-7.976563-29.101562 5.800782-10.238281 18.855469-13.84375 29.097657-7.976563l197.953125 112.851563c10.21875 5.824219 13.800781 18.859375 7.976562 29.101562-3.945312 6.910157-11.15625 10.773438-18.558594 10.773438zm0 0"/></svg>
							</a>
						</li>
					</ul>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
	<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
		<div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black">
						<div class="margin-bottom-2"><h2 class="heading-14">Details</h2></div>
			<div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3">
				<div class="grid-col-4">
					<div class="subheading">Last Updated</div>
				</div>
				<div class="grid-col-8">
					Nov 29, 2023				</div>
			</div>
						<div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3">
				<div class="grid-col-4">
					<div class="subheading">Editor</div>
				</div>
				<div class="grid-col-8">
					Andrea Gianopoulos				</div>
			</div>
							<div class="grid-row margin-bottom-3">
				<div class="grid-col-4">
					<div class="subheading">Contact</div>
				</div>
				<div class="grid-col-8">
				<div class="margin-bottom-3"><div> </div><div></div></div>				</div>
			</div>
								<div class="grid-row">
				<div class="grid-col-4">
				<div class="subheading">Location</div>
				</div>
				<div class="grid-col-8">
											Goddard Space Flight Center									</div>
			</div>
				</div>
	</div>
		<div class="grid-col-12 desktop:grid-col-5 padding-right-4 margin-bottom-5 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
		<div class="padding-top-3 border-top-1px border-color-carbon-black ">
			<div class="margin-bottom-2"><h2 class="heading-14">Related Terms</h2></div>
						<ul class="article-tags">
				<li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/astrophysics/" rel="noopener">Astrophysics</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/astrophysics/" rel="noopener">Astrophysics Division</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/goddard/">Goddard Space Flight Center</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/mission/hubble" rel="noopener">Hubble Space Telescope</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/nasa-missions/">Missions</a></li><li class="article-tag"><a href="https://science.nasa.gov/about-us/" rel="noopener">Science Mission Directorate</a></li>			</ul>
					</div>
	</div>
		</div>
</section>
	</div>

<div id="" class="hds-topic-cards nasa-gb-align-full maxw-full width-full padding-y-6 padding-x-3 color-mode-dark hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-topic-cards">		<div class="grid-container grid-container-block-lg padding-x-0">
			<div class="grid-row flex-align-center margin-bottom-3">
				<div class="desktop:grid-col-8 margin-bottom-2 desktop:margin-bottom-0">
					<div class="label color-carbon-60 margin-bottom-2">Keep Exploring</div>
					<h2 class="heading-36 line-height-sm">Discover More Topics From NASA</h2>
				</div>
			</div>
				<div class="grid-row grid-gap-2 hds-topic-cards-wrapper">
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/hubble/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<h3 class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Hubble Space Telescope</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</h3>
							<p class="margin-bottom-0 margin-top-2 color-carbon-20-important">Since its 1990 launch, the Hubble Space Telescope has changed our fundamental understanding of the universe.</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1512" height="1536" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?w=1512" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536 not-transparent" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;--dominant-color: #51596a;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg 4031w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=295,300 295w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=768,780 768w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=1008,1024 1008w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=1512,1536 1512w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=2016,2048 2016w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=50,50 50w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=394,400 394w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=591,600 591w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=886,900 886w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=1181,1200 1181w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/hubble-space-telescope-hst-6.jpg?resize=1969,2000 1969w" sizes="(max-width: 1512px) 100vw, 1512px" data-has-transparency="false" data-dominant-color="51596a" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/astrophysics/focus-areas/what-are-galaxies/stories/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<p class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Galaxies Stories</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1280" height="1423" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?w=1280" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536 not-transparent" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;--dominant-color: #1d1514;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp 1280w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?resize=270,300 270w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?resize=768,854 768w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?resize=921,1024 921w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?resize=360,400 360w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?resize=540,600 540w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?resize=810,900 810w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-abells0740-opo0708a-jpg.webp?resize=1079,1200 1079w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" data-has-transparency="false" data-dominant-color="1d1514" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/james-webb-space-telescope/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<h3 class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>James Webb Space Telescope</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</h3>
							<p class="margin-bottom-0 margin-top-2 color-carbon-20-important">Webb is the premier observatory of the next decade, serving thousands of astronomers worldwide. It studies every phase in the…</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1536" height="890" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?w=1536" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536 not-transparent" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;--dominant-color: #5b4850;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp 3600w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=300,174 300w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=768,445 768w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=1024,593 1024w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=1536,890 1536w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=2048,1186 2048w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=400,232 400w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=600,348 600w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=900,521 900w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=1200,695 1200w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/main-image-star-forming-region-carina-nircam-final-5mb-1-jpeg.webp?resize=2000,1158 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1536px) 100vw, 1536px" data-has-transparency="false" data-dominant-color="5b4850" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
					<a href="https://science.nasa.gov/astrophysics/focus-areas/how-do-stars-form-and-evolve/stories/" class="mobile:grid-col-12 tablet:grid-col-6 desktop:grid-col-3 topic-card margin-bottom-4 desktop:margin-bottom-0" rel="noopener">
				<div class="hds-topic-card hds-cover-wrapper cover-hover-zoom bg-carbon-black">
					<div class="skrim-overlay skrim-overlay-dark skrim-left mobile-skrim-top padding-3 display-flex flex-align-end flex-justify-start z-200">
						<div>
													<p class="hds-topic-card-heading heading-29 color-spacesuit-white line-height-sm margin-top-0 margin-bottom-1">
								<span>Stars Stories</span>
								<svg viewBox="0 0 32 32" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><circle class="color-nasa-red" cx="16" cy="16" r="16"></circle><path d="M8 16.956h12.604l-3.844 4.106 1.252 1.338L24 16l-5.988-6.4-1.252 1.338 3.844 4.106H8v1.912z" class="color-spacesuit-white"></path></svg>
							</p>
													</div>
					</div>
											<figure class="hds-media-background  "><img loading="lazy" width="1280" height="1141" src="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?w=1280" class="attachment-1536x1536 size-1536x1536 not-transparent" alt="" decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;--dominant-color: #373d57;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp 1280w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?resize=300,267 300w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?resize=768,685 768w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?resize=1024,913 1024w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?resize=400,357 400w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?resize=600,535 600w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?resize=900,802 900w, https://smd-cms.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/hubble-ngc3603-opo1022a-jpg.webp?resize=1200,1070 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" data-has-transparency="false" data-dominant-color="373d57" /></figure>									</div>
			</a>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Announcing the New Heliophysics Division Director </title>
            <link>
                https://science.nasa.gov/directorates/smd/announcing-the-new-heliophysics-division-director/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 19:17:01 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Science Mission Directorate]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">
                https://science.nasa.gov/directorates/smd/announcing-the-new-heliophysics-division-director/</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[November 29, 2023 NASA has selected Dr. Joseph Westlake to fill the position of Heliophysics Division Director. Joe will join the Science Mission Directorate and assume his new role on Jan. 16, 2024.  I am pleased to have Joe take on the role as the Heliophysics Division Director. Joe has a strong background in heliophysics […]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="padding-top-5 padding-bottom-3 width-full maxw-full hds-module hds-module-full wp-block-nasa-blocks-article-intro"> 

	<div class="width-full maxw-full article-header">
		<div class="margin-bottom-2 width-full maxw-full">
			<p class="label carbon-60 margin-0 margin-bottom-3 padding-0">3 min read</p>
			<h1 class="display-48 margin-bottom-2">Announcing the New Heliophysics Division Director </h1>
		</div>	
	</div>

	</div>


<h4 class="wp-block-heading">November 29, 2023</h4>



<p>NASA has selected Dr. Joseph Westlake to fill the position of Heliophysics Division Director. Joe will join the Science Mission Directorate and assume his new role on Jan. 16, 2024. </p>



<p>I am pleased to have Joe take on the role as the Heliophysics Division Director. Joe has a strong background in heliophysics and planetary science and has already made significant contributions to our efforts by supporting several NASA missions including the Magnetospheric Multiscale mission, the Van Allen Probes, Parker Solar Probe, the Interstellar Boundary Explorer mission, the Juno mission, Cassini and the European Space Agency’s Juice mission to Ganymede. </p>



<p>Joe brings with him more than 18 years of scientific, technical, management, and programmatic experience in heliophysics, astrophysics, and planetary science. He is coming to us from the Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory (JHUAPL) where he works as a researcher and project scientist for the Interstellar Mapping and Acceleration Probe mission and principal investigator for the Plasma Instrument for Magnetic Sounding, or PIMS, instrument destined for Jupiter’s moon, Europa, onboard the Europa Clipper mission.  </p>



<p>“I’m very excited to join NASA as the Division Director for Heliophysics,” said Westlake. “I look forward to diving in and working with the vibrant community of scientists and engineers that are uncovering the mysteries of our star.” </p>



<p>In 2024, the National Academies will release a new Decadal Survey that lays out a strategy to advance scientific understanding of the Sun, Sun-Earth connections and the origins of space weather, the Sun’s interactions with other bodies in the solar system, the interplanetary medium, and the interstellar medium; Joe’s experience across several scientific disciplines, as well as his leadership and technical experience, uniquely qualifies him for this critical leadership position in the Science Mission Directorate as we embark on an exciting new decade of solar and space physics. </p>



<p>I extend my sincere appreciation to Peg Luce who led the Division for nearly a year while the director position was vacant; she has done a stellar job. With nearly 10 years as the deputy director, Peg’s exceptional efforts have brought significant strides within Science Mission Directorate and the broader scientific community. I am thrilled she will continue serving as the Heliophysics Division Deputy Director and helping Joe usher the division into this new era. </p>



<p>“The Sun touches everything and the science of heliophysics is helping us unlock its mysteries,” said Peg Luce, deputy division director, Heliophysics Division at NASA Headquarters in Washington. “Joe’s unique experience and insight will help guide the division as we usher in solar max, launch a host of new heliophysics missions, and flow through the Heliophysics Big Year.” </p>



<p>Please join me in welcoming Joe to Headquarters! </p>
]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
        <item>
            <title>The Beginnings of a Sunrise</title>
            <link>https://www.nasa.gov/image-article/the-beginnings-of-a-sunrise/</link>

            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Monika Luabeya]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 17:51:21 +0000</pubDate>
            <category><![CDATA[Astronauts]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Earth]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Humans in Space]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[International Space Station (ISS)]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Jasmin Moghbeli]]></category>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nasa.gov/?post_type=image-article&#038;p=572519</guid>

            <description><![CDATA[City lights stretch across the United States like a string of holiday lights in this image taken from the International Space Station on Nov. 10, 2023. At far left, the lights of Chicago, Illinois, are outlined by Lake Michigan. At far right, the Dallas/Fort Worth metropolitan area shines through the clouds while the sun&#8217;s first [&#8230;]]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="" class="hds-media hds-module wp-block-image"><div class="margin-left-auto margin-right-auto nasa-block-align-inline"><div class="hds-media-wrapper margin-left-auto margin-right-auto"><figure class="hds-media-inner hds-cover-wrapper hds-media-ratio-cover "><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1365" src="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?w=2048" class="attachment-2048x2048 size-2048x2048" alt="In the distance, small points of light can be seen against the darkness of space. The sun&#039;s rays peek over Earth, creating a blue haze tinged with orange. On Earth, the city lights of Chicago, Illinois, (far left) and the Dallas/Fort Worth metropolitan area (far right) shine." decoding="async" style="transform: scale(1.2); transform-origin: 50% 50%; object-position: 50% 50%; object-fit: cover;" block_context="nasa-block" srcset="https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg 5568w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=400,267 400w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=600,400 600w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://www.nasa.gov/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/53332473614-7e5c400698-o.jpg?resize=2000,1333 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /></figure><figcaption class="hds-caption padding-y-2"><div class="hds-credits">NASA / Jasmin Moghbeli</div></figcaption></div></div></div>


<p>City lights stretch across the United States like a string of holiday lights in this image taken from the International Space Station on Nov. 10, 2023. At far left, the lights of Chicago, Illinois, are outlined by Lake Michigan. At far right, the Dallas/Fort Worth metropolitan area shines through the clouds while the sun&#8217;s first rays start to light up Earth&#8217;s atmosphere (at top).</p>



<p>Since the space station became operational in November 2000, <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/research/station-science-101/earth-observation/">crew members have produced hundreds of thousands of images of the land, oceans, and atmosphere&nbsp;of Earth</a>. Their photographs of Earth record how the planet changes over time due to human activity and natural events. This allows scientists to monitor disasters and direct response on the&nbsp;ground and study phenomena, from the movement of glaciers to urban wildlife.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/nasa2explore/albums/72157715276332203" rel="noopener">Explore more images of cities at night taken by astronauts on the space station.</a></p>



<p><em>Image Credit: NASA/Jasmin Moghbeli</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>


        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>